<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook45-profile.xsl"
                 type="text/xml" title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY copy "©">
<!ENTITY reg "®">
<!ENTITY tm "™">
<!ENTITY sm "℠">
]>

  <sect1 id="sec.structure">
    <title>Structure and Markup</title>

    <para>Structure your documentation by tasks relevant to the user instead of
      providing reference documentation by describing each part of the user
      interface individually. In most cases, it is unnecessary to describe
      every minor functionality of a product. Describe what a product can do
      rather than its limitations.
    </para>

    <sect2 id="sec.admonition">
      <title>Admonitory and Advisory Paragraphs</title>

      <para>To make readers aware of potential problems and recent changes, or
        to give them tips, use an admonition element. Avoid using more than one
        admonition per page of PDF output.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title><sgmltag class="emptytag">warning</sgmltag></title>
            <para>Use these elements to warn of security issues, potential loss
              of data, damage to hardware, or physical hazards. Warnings must
              always precede the action to which they apply.
            </para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title><sgmltag class="emptytag">important</sgmltag></title>
            <para>Use these elements to give vital information.</para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title><sgmltag class="emptytag">tip</sgmltag></title>
            <para>Use these elements to introduce guidelines or give
              tips.
            </para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title><sgmltag class="emptytag">note</sgmltag></title>
            <para>Use these elements to highlight software version differences.
            </para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Follow these rules when writing admonitions:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Add a <sgmltag class="emptytag">title</sgmltag> to
            admonitions. In the title, state the subject of the admonition
            and, in the case of a <sgmltag class="emptytag">warning</sgmltag>,
            also the source of danger.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis><sgmltag class="emptytag">warning</sgmltag> or
            <sgmltag class="emptytag">important</sgmltag>:</emphasis>
            In the first paragraph, clearly state possible consequences
            of ignoring the danger.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis><sgmltag class="emptytag">warning</sgmltag> or
            <sgmltag class="emptytag">important</sgmltag>:</emphasis>
            In the second paragraph, explain how to
            avoid the danger. If there are multiple ways to avoid a danger,
            using a unordered list is helpful. In case multiple steps need
            to be taken to avoid a danger, use an ordered list or use a
            cross reference to refer to another part of the documentation.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <example>
        <title>An Example of a Warning</title>
        <screen>&lt;warning&gt;
  &lt;title&gt;Creating File Systems Can Take Several Hours&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;para&gt;Interrupting this process will result in a corrupt file system
    and an unusable installation.
  &lt;/para&gt;
  &lt;para&gt;Always wait until formatting has finished.&lt;/para&gt;
&lt;/warning&gt;</screen>
      </example>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.application">
      <title>Application Names</title>

      <para>When referring to an application, add a
          <sgmltag class="emptytag">phrase role="productname"</sgmltag> element
          around it. This will not result in a visual change but disables
          hyphenation:
      </para>
      <screen>&lt;phrase role="productname"&gt;LibreOffice&lt;/phrase&gt; is an office suite.</screen>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.callout">
      <title>Callouts</title>

      <para>Add the <sgmltag class="emptytag">co</sgmltag> elements directly
        after the part of a screen that you want to annotate. Do not try to
        align them above the part of a screen to annotate.
        Do not use more than ten callouts per example.
      </para>
      <example id="ex.callout">
        <title>A Configuration File with Callouts</title>
        <screen>color white/blue black/light-gray <co id="col"/>
default 0 <co id="def"/>
timeout 8 <co id="time"/>
gfxmenu (hd0,0)/boot/message

title SUSE Linux Enterprise
    kernel (hd0,0)/boot/vmlinuz root=/dev/hda1 vga=0x31a selinux=0
    splash=silent resume=/dev/hda2 desktop elevator=as  showopts
    initrd (hd0,0)/boot/initrd

title Disk
    root (fd0)
    chainloader +1</screen>
        <calloutlist>
          <callout arearefs="col">
            <para>Color definitions to be used by the
              <phrase role="productname">GRUB</phrase> menu.
            </para>
          </callout>
          <callout arearefs="def">
            <para>Define the default option.</para>
          </callout>
          <callout arearefs="time">
            <para>Select a time-out after which booting starts automatically.
            </para>
          </callout>
        </calloutlist>
      </example>
      <para>For details on the markup of this element, refer to
        <xref linkend="sec.markup.block.callouts"/>.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.command_line">
      <title>Command Line Input and Output</title>

      <para>When dealing with user input and system output shorter than 30
        characters, format it with an inline element, such as
        <sgmltag class="emptytag">command</sgmltag> or
        <sgmltag class="emptytag">filename</sgmltag>. In all other cases,
        close the current paragraph and enclose it in a
        <sgmltag class="emptytag">screen</sgmltag> element.
      </para>

      <sect3 id="sec.command">
        <title>Commands</title>

        <para>Make sure to capitalize commands exactly as they are executed.
          Commands can be embedded in running text or
          presented as part of a screen environment. In running text,
          use <sgmltag class="emptytag">command</sgmltag> when referring
          to an actual command you would use on a command line:
        </para>
        <literallayout>To start LibreOffice from the command line, use <command>loffice</command>.</literallayout>
        <para>Nest options, surrounded by an
          <sgmltag class="emptytag">option</sgmltag> element,
          inside the command element. Options can also be used in
          text, separately from <sgmltag class="emptytag">command</sgmltag>. See
          <xref linkend="sec.markup.inline.commands"/>.
        </para>
        <para>Use markup for commands even inside
          <sgmltag class="emptytag">screen</sgmltag>
          environments.
        </para>
        <para>See also <xref linkend="sec.prompt"/>.
        </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="sec.placeholder">
        <title>Placeholders</title>

        <para>To mark up text that readers need to replace, use the
          <sgmltag class="emptytag">replaceable</sgmltag> element.
        </para>
            <screen>To list the contents of a directory, execute
&lt;command&gt;ls &lt;replaceable&gt;directory&lt;/replaceable&gt;&lt;/command&gt;.</screen>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="sec.variable">
        <title>Variable Names</title>

          <para>Reference to names of variables rather than to their value.
          </para>
          <screen>To select another display manager, start the YaST sysconfig editor
and change the value of &lt;variable&gt;DISPLAYMANAGER&lt;/variable&gt;.</screen>
      </sect3>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.crossreference">
      <title>Cross References</title>

      <para> Use the <sgmltag class="emptytag">xref</sgmltag> element (read:
        <quote>cross ref</quote>) when referring to an appendix, chapter,
        example, figure, part, preface, section, table, or question and answer
        set. The referenced element needs an
        <sgmltag class="attribute">id</sgmltag> attribute. When
        referencing these elements, do not insert a text label like
        <quote>appendix</quote>, <quote>chapter</quote>, <quote>part</quote>,
        <quote>preface</quote>, <quote>section</quote>, <quote>table</quote>,
        <quote>figure</quote>, and <quote>example</quote>. These are inserted
        automatically.
      </para>
      <para>Do not insert references to single paragraphs
        (<sgmltag class="emptytag">para</sgmltag>). If you need to reference
        a list, insert <sgmltag class="emptytag">id</sgmltag> and
        <sgmltag class="emptytag">xreflabel</sgmltag>.
      </para>
      <para>Other types of references to resources are described in
        <xref linkend="sec.other_external"/> and
        <xref linkend="sec.link"/>.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.link">
      <title>External Links</title>

      <para>Where possible, collect links in a
        <quote>For More Information</quote> section at the end of the chapter.
        This will help users focus on your documentation instead of leading
        them to other resources before they had a chance to read the end
        of the sentence.
      </para>
      <para>To mark up multiple links, create an
        <sgmltag class="emptytag">itemizedlist</sgmltag> around
        them. Do not use a list environment for only one link.
        If you need to present a large number of links, group them by topic and
        create a separate list environment for each group. Provide a
        comprehensive title for each of the groups or an introductory sentence.
      </para>
      <para>Use the <sgmltag class="emptytag">ulink</sgmltag> element to mark up
        URLs that can be opened with a Web browser, such as
        <ulink url="http://www.suse.de"/>.
        Always add the correct protocol prefix (for example,
        <literal>http://</literal>),
        otherwise links will not work. Never use <sgmltag>filename</sgmltag>
        for a link, as that would both disable the link checker and make the
        link unclickable. Avoid entering a text label between the
        <sgmltag class="emptytag">ulink</sgmltag> start and end tags.
      </para>
      <para>Try to make URLs as short as possible before pasting them into your
        documentation. Many long URLs can be shortened by leaving away
        non-essential pieces of them. This is often the case with search URLs
        or URLs of Internet news media. If a Web site provides a built-in URL
        shortener, use that. Do not resort to using external URL shorteners, as
        that both hides the actual destination a link will take the user to and
        introduces an extra element of uncertainty, as the shortening service
        may disappear or become unreliable in the future.
      </para>
      <para>Do not use <sgmltag class="emptytag">ulink</sgmltag> to link to SUSE
        documentation outside of the current document set. Instead, use the
        appropriate entity for the book title. Always reference the book
        itself, as chapter names can change.
      </para>
      <para>Where possible, provide translators with localized versions of
        links in the comments of the source file.
      </para>
      <para>Other types of references to resources are described in
        <xref linkend="sec.crossreference"/> and
        <xref linkend="sec.other_external"/>.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.example">
      <title>Examples</title>

      <para>Use examples to illustrate complex processes.
        The rules established in <xref linkend="sec.graphic"/> also
        apply to examples.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Examples are used to present long commands, commands
            together with their output, lines of code, configuration files,
            excerpts of configuration files, and output, such as system
            messages.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Never indent text inside
            <sgmltag class="emptytag">screen</sgmltag>
            elements as you do in other XML elements. All whitespace inside
            <sgmltag class="emptytag">screen</sgmltag> elements shows up
            verbatim.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Only use examples where they are necessary for understanding
            the documentation.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Always give examples a title and an ID.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <example id="ex.call_ps">
        <title>Calling ps to Get Process Information</title>
        <screen><prompt>tux &gt; </prompt><command>ps <option>-xa</option></command>

5170 ?        S      0:00 kdeinit: khotkeys
5172 ?        S      0:02 kdeinit: kdesktop
5174 ?        S      0:04 kdeinit: kicker
5177 ?        S      0:00 kdeinit: kpowersave
5179 ?        S      0:00 kdeinit: klipper</screen>
      </example>
      <para>For details on displaying computer input and output, refer to
        <xref linkend="sec.command_line"/>.
        For details on markup, refer to
        <xref linkend="sec.markup.block.examples"/>.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.glossary">
      <title>Glossaries</title>
      <para>An optional glossary contains terms and their definitions. Make sure
        that the glossary entries are appropriate to the intended audience. Define
        unfamiliar terms and specialized jargon.
      </para>
      <para>Define infinitive forms of verbs and singular nouns. Use lowercase for
        the term unless it is a proper noun.
      </para>
      <para>Use cross-references to link acronyms with their written out forms.
        Define the written out form. Use a <emphasis>See</emphasis> reference for
        the acronym form to link it to the defined written out form.
      </para>
      <para>The markup for a glossary entry is shown in
        <xref linkend="ex.glossary"/>.
      </para>
      <example id="ex.glossary">
        <title>A Typical Example of a Glossary</title>
        <screen>&lt;glossary&gt;
&lt;title&gt;Glossary&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;glossentry&gt;
    &lt;glossterm id="gt.extensible"&gt;Extensible Markup Language&lt;/glossterm&gt;
    &lt;glossdef&gt;
      &lt;para&gt;A markup language that defines a set of rules for encoding
        documents in a format that is both human-readable and machine-readable.
      &lt;/para&gt;
    &lt;/glossdef&gt;
  &lt;/glossentry&gt;
  &lt;glossentry&gt;
    &lt;glossterm&gt;XML&lt;/glossterm&gt;
    &lt;glossdef&gt;
      &lt;para&gt;See also &lt;xref linkend="gt.extensible"/&gt;.&lt;/para&gt;
    &lt;/glossdef&gt;
  &lt;/glossentry&gt;
&lt;/glossary&gt;</screen>
      </example>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.figure">
      <title>Figures</title>

      <para>For figures within lists or procedures, use the
        <sgmltag class="emptytag">informalfigure</sgmltag> element. In all
        other cases, use the <sgmltag class="emptytag">figure</sgmltag> element.
        Reference figures from the text by means of a cross reference.
        For more information, see <xref linkend="sec.crossreference"/>.
      </para>
      <para>All referenced image files must have a lowercase alphanumeric
        file name.
      </para>

      <sect3 id="sec.graphic">
        <title>Graphics</title>

        <para>Keep graphics as simple as possible. Use as little text as
          possible. To allow for translation,
          reserve twice as much space for runs of text as the English version
          of it consumes.
        </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="sec.screenshot">
        <title>Screenshots</title>

        <para>Use screenshots to illustrate complex situations in which
          the user cannot easily follow the instructions otherwise.
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Be selective. Only illustrate steps in which meaningful user
              interactions are necessary. Do not create screenshots of progress
              bars or confirmation windows. In most cases, it is
              unnecessary to create a screenshot of every step of an
              instruction.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Make sure screenshots focus on what they are supposed to
              illustrate. When documenting application windows, create a
              screenshot of the window only. When documenting web applications,
              only reproduce the contents of the tab, instead of the entire
              browser window.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Avoid creating screenshots of windows higher or
              wider than 800&nbsp;pixels at 96&nbsp;pixels per inch. When
              creating screenshots of applications scaled for a higher
              pixel-per-inch count, apply a proportionally larger maximum window
              size.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Create screenshots that are recognizable to readers. For
              instance, create screenshots of KDE applications on a KDE desktop
              with the default KDE theme and disable any toolbar modifications
              you may have made.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Use grayscale font antialiasing (default on SUSE
              operating systems). Subpixel font antialiasing creates colored
              letter edges on some screens and in print.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Where applicable, follow the rules in
              <xref linkend="sec.name"/>.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Avoid editing screenshots. If you need to edit a
              screenshot, use the
              <phrase role="programname">Shutter</phrase> application. To
              anonymize portions of a screenshot, use the
              <guimenu>Pixelize</guimenu> tool. To highlight parts of a
              screenshot, use the <guimenu>Rectangle</guimenu> tool or the
              <guimenu>Arrow</guimenu> tool. Avoid using callouts. Never add
              text or freely drawn objects. Always select colors providing a
              good contrast with their background.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.heading">
      <title>Headings</title>
      <para>Each level of heading contain have two or more subheadings. Lone
        subheadings are not allowed. Make headings in a group parallel by using
        a similar structure for the wording.
      </para>
      <para>Keep headings short and simple. Do not use both an acronym and the
        written-out form in a heading.
      </para>
      <para>Provide content between a heading and its subheadings. In some
        cases, this is only a small paragraph of introductory information.
        In other cases, more information can be provided.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.index">
      <title>Indexes</title>
      <para>Insert index terms as close to the relevant text as possible.
        When more than five paragraphs belong to a topic, use a page range.
        Nest index terms up to two levels deep.
      </para>
      <para>When indexing, look for information a user is likely to be trying to
        find. Adapt breadth and depth of included index terms for a given
        topic to the weight it has within the manual. Never index
        <quote>For More Information</quote> sections, abstracts,
        or commands that only appear as means to a different end.
      </para>
      <para>Be consistent in the terms you index. However,
        consider that users might not have the exact same terms in mind as you
        do, especially when it comes to highly technical words or brands.
        Write nouns in the plural. Write verbs in a gerund form
        (<emphasis>-ing</emphasis>). Use sentence-style capitalization for
        index terms.
      </para>
      <para>If an entry has six or more page references, try to subsume them
        as subentries under a single entry. If an entry has only a single
        subentry, consider deleting the subentry.
      </para>
      <para>Check for inconsistencies that result in multiple items in
        the index. Check all <emphasis>see</emphasis> and
        <emphasis>see also</emphasis> references for consistency.
        Items should not have both a page and a
        <emphasis>see</emphasis> reference. Where possible, avoid using page
        references and <emphasis>see also</emphasis> together.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.list">
      <title>Lists</title>

      <para>SUSE and openSUSE documentation uses the following types of lists
        (the respective XML elements are given in parentheses):
      </para>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Bullet Lists (<sgmltag class="emptytag">itemizedlist</sgmltag>)
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>See
              <ulink url="http://www.docbook.org/tdg/en/html/itemizedlist.html"/>
              for details of markup.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Numbered Lists (<sgmltag class="emptytag">orderedlist</sgmltag>)
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>See
              <ulink url="http://www.docbook.org/tdg/en/html/orderedlist.html"/>
              for details of markup.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Descriptive Lists
            (<sgmltag class="emptytag">variablelist</sgmltag>)
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>See
              <ulink url="http://www.docbook.org/tdg/en/html/variablelist.html"/>
              for details on markup.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      <para>Consider the following general rules when creating or editing list
        environments:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>List environments should be used cautiously. Their markup is
            quite distinct and overusing them might disrupt the text flow.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Always introduce a list in the text. If needed for reference or
            better coordination with the related text, add an optional title
            and an <sgmltag class="attribute">id</sgmltag> attribute.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>A list must contain at least two items. If items are short
            and simple in structure, consider incorporating them in the
            flowing text instead of creating a list environment.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use sentence-style capitalization for the list items. Use
            title-style capitalization for terms in descriptive lists.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>When using multiple sentences as a list item, end all items
            in that list with a period.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Make sure that the items are grammatically parallel
            constructions providing a pattern that makes it easier
            to follow the text.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Never nest more than three lists within each other. In such cases,
        try to restructure the information using a combination of
        lists and running texts.
      </para>

      <sect3 id="sec.bullet">
        <title>Bullet Lists</title>

        <para>Bullet lists are often used to provide an overview of information
          or to introduce or summarize information. They should be used when
          the order of list items is irrelevant.
        </para>
        <para>If needed, assign an <sgmltag class="attribute">id</sgmltag>
          attribute to an itemized list and add a title to reference it.
          Individual list items may be referenced by assigning an
          <sgmltag class="attribute">id</sgmltag> and an
          <sgmltag class="attribute">xreflabel</sgmltag> attribute. The entry is
          then identified by the value of
          <sgmltag class="attribute">id</sgmltag>
          and the value of <sgmltag class="attribute">xreflabel</sgmltag> is
          printed as the label of this item. See
          <xref linkend="sec.crossreference"/> and
          <xref linkend="sec.markup.inline.referencing"/> for detailed
          information.
        </para>
        <example id="ex.bulllist">
          <title>A Bullet List</title>
          <para>The following operating systems are supported:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Windows 2000 and newer</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Linux, Kernel 2.4 and newer</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>FreeBSD 7 and newer</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </example>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="sec.numbered">
        <title>Numbered Lists</title>

        <para>Use numbered lists when items have a strict order, hierarchy, or
          importance. If order is not relevant, use a bullet list or a
          descriptive list. Do not use numbered lists to describe procedures.
          Complex sequential actions are better described by means of the
          procedure environment (see <xref linkend="sec.procedure"/>
          for a detailed description).
        </para>
        <para>If needed, assign an <sgmltag class="attribute">id</sgmltag>
          attribute to a numbered list and add a title to it in order to
          reference it. Individual list items may be referenced by assigning an
          <sgmltag class="attribute">id</sgmltag> and
          <sgmltag class="attribute">xreflabel</sgmltag> attribute. The
          entry is then identified by the value of
          <sgmltag class="attribute">id</sgmltag> and the value of
          <sgmltag class="attribute">xreflabel</sgmltag> is printed as the label
          of this item. See <xref linkend="sec.crossreference"/> and
          <xref linkend="sec.markup.inline.referencing"/> for detailed
          information.
        </para>
        <example id="ex.numbered">
          <title>A Numbered List</title>
          <para>Make sure the following requirements are met before trying to
            set up an Apache Web server:
          </para>
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>The network connection of the machine is configured
                properly.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>The exact system time of the machine is maintained by
                synchronizing with a time server. This is necessary because
                parts of the HTTP protocol depend on the correct time.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>The latest security updates are installed. If in doubt,
                run an online update.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>The default Web server port (port 80) is opened in the
                firewall. For this, configure the SUSEFirewall2 to allow the
                service <guimenu>HTTP Server</guimenu> in the external zone.
                This can be done using YaST.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </example>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="sec.descriptive">
        <title>Descriptive Lists</title>

        <para>Use descriptive lists when defining terms or describing options.
          Each item of a descriptive list contains a short term that is then
          further explained by means of an explanatory paragraph.
        </para>
        <para>Use title-style capitalization for the term. Use sentence-style
          for the list item.
        </para>
        <para>You may assign an <sgmltag class="attribute">id</sgmltag>
          attribute to the list and add a title to it in order to reference it.
          Individual list items may be referenced by assigning an
          <sgmltag class="attribute">id</sgmltag>. The entry is then identified
          by the value of <sgmltag class="attribute">id</sgmltag> and
          referenced by the term.
        </para>
        <example id="ex.varlist">
          <title>A Descriptive List</title>
          <para>This book consists of several parts:</para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Installation</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>Learn about the installation and initial configuration
                  of a Linux system.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>System</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>Get a basic understanding of the system components.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </example>
      </sect3>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.keyboard">
      <title>Keys and Key Combinations</title>

      <para>Capitalize all keys as printed on a standard keyboard. Following
        this rule, capitalize all letter keys. If you need to refer to a
        capitalized character, use
        <keycombo><keycap function="shift"/><keycap>Z</keycap></keycombo>,
        for example. Introduce this convention by means of the
        <quote>Typographical Conventions</quote> section of the introduction.
      </para>
      <para>Localization of the identifiers for both modifiers and
        special keys can be handled by DocBook itself, if you use the
        <sgmltag class="emptytag">keycap</sgmltag> element and an appropriate
        <literal>function</literal> value. For details, refer to
        <xref linkend="sec.markup.inline.keys"/>.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.other_external">
      <title>References to Other External Resources</title>

      <para>References to man pages and info pages should generally be
        made in the format <quote>the man page of
        <command>command</command></quote> or
        <quote>the info page of <command>command</command></quote>. In a
        situation where the category of the page is needed, add
        for example <quote>(<command>man 9 command</command>)</quote>
        to the end.
      </para>
      <para>To reference file names, use the
        <sgmltag class="emptytag">filename</sgmltag>
        element. To reference e-mail addresses, use the
        <sgmltag class="emptytag">email</sgmltag>
        element. In either case, do not include a protocol prefix, that is
        <literal>file://</literal> or <literal>mailto:</literal>, respectively.
      </para>
      <para>Insert references to external (not SUSE or openSUSE) physical
        books in the format <quote>Title by Author (ISBN #00000000).</quote>
        Inclusion of the ISBN is optional. Place the title in a
        <sgmltag class="emptytag">citetitle</sgmltag> element. For example:
      </para>
      <screen>&lt;citetitle&gt;Indexing Books&lt;/citetitle&gt; by Nancy C. Mulvany
(ISBN 0-226-55014-1) is a useful guide to indexing.</screen>
      <para>It is useful to provide language-specific references in the
        translated books. If the authors know of language-specific versions,
        they can include them in comments for translators. As time permits,
        translators should look for corresponding language-specific resources.
        For URLs, provide only the language-specific version of a site. Use the
        English as a fall-back. For books, provide the title of the translated
        version along with the original title if such a translation exists.
      </para>
      <para>Other types of references to resources are described in
        <xref linkend="sec.crossreference"/> and
        <xref linkend="sec.link"/>.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.procedure">
    <title>Procedures</title>

      <para>Use procedures to describe sequential tasks. A procedure
        consists of the following elements:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>A title and an <sgmltag class="attribute">id</sgmltag>
            attribute.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>An introductory phrase establishing the purpose of the
            procedure. If the procedure is otherwise the only element in
            its section, place the introductory phrase before the procedure.
            If necessary, add any preconditions of the operation after the
            introductory phrase.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Short, simple steps and substeps describing the actions to
            be performed. See also <xref linkend="sec.structure_sentence"/>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Describe alternative actions inside a substep element
        containing steps linked by <quote>or.</quote> Apply a
        <sgmltag class="attribute">performance=optional</sgmltag>
        attribute to optional steps.
      </para>
      <para>Steps may contain a link to an explanatory
        subsection providing further details on the step.
      </para>
      <procedure id="pro.useradd">
        <title>Adding Users with YaST</title>
        <para>To add a new user to the system, perform the following steps:
        </para>
        <step>
          <para>Open <guimenu>YaST</guimenu>.</para>
        </step>
        <step performance="optional">
          <para>If you are asked, type the password of the
            <systemitem>root</systemitem> user and click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
          </para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>Click <guimenu>User and Group Management</guimenu>.</para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>To open the <guimenu>Add a New User</guimenu> dialog, click
            <guimenu>Add</guimenu>.
          </para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>Type in the user data and click <guimenu>Create</guimenu>.
          </para>
        </step>
        <step performance="optional">
          <para>Repeat from the third step to add more
            users.
          </para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>Leave the YaST module by clicking <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
          </para>
        </step>
      </procedure>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.product">
      <title>Products and Trademarks</title>

      <para>Always use the preferred product name instead of, for instance, an
        acronym. When referring to a product, add a
        <sgmltag class="emptytag">phrase role="productname"</sgmltag> element
        around it.
        This will not result in a visual change but disables hyphenation:
      </para>
      <screen>&lt;phrase role="productname"&gt;LibreOffice&lt;/phrase&gt; is an office suite.</screen>
      <para>Most products referenced in the documentation are trademarked.
        Follow these rules when dealing with these terms:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Never use trademarks in headings.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Only use the marked version on the first occurrence of the
            product name in a chapter.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Only use the &reg;, &tm;, or &sm; marks for
            <phrase role="companyname">Attachmate</phrase> products.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use an * (asterisk) for all service marks or trademarks of
            third-party companies. This both acknowledges the service mark
            or trademark of the other company and protects SUSE in case the
            protection of the brand changes in any way.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.prompt">
      <title>Prompts</title>

      <para>When documenting commands entered into Bash with a
        <sgmltag class="emptytag">screen</sgmltag> element, always prefix them
        with a prompt marked up this way:
      </para>
      <screen>&lt;prompt&gt;tux &amp;gt; &lt;/prompt&gt;&lt;command&gt;ls&lt;/command&gt;</screen>
      <para>Never include a host name or path in your prompts to avoid making
        them longer than necessary. The first restricted user should always use
        the name <emphasis>tux</emphasis>. For other names of restricted users,
        see <xref linkend="sec.bias"/>.
      </para>
      <para>Avoid using root prompts in your documentation by using the
        <command>sudo</command> command where applicable. If you do need a root prompt,
        always mark it up as following:
      </para>
      <screen>&lt;prompt&gt;root # &lt;/prompt&gt;&lt;command&gt;yast&lt;/command&gt;</screen>
      <para>When documenting prompts other than the one of Bash, use a
        custom prompt that is as generic as possible.
      </para>
      <para>For consistency, it is helpful to create entities for the prompts
        used in your documentation. To learn more, refer to
        <xref linkend="sec.entity"/>.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.table">
      <title>Tables</title>

      <para>Use tables to present large numbers of similar facts. Tables are
        easy to scan and compare. Always keep tables simple enough to not
        require long explanations even for readers unfamiliar with the topic.
      </para>
      <para>A table always has a title and should have an
        <sgmltag class="attribute">id</sgmltag> attribute.
      </para>
      <para>Value and description pairs are better handled by means of a
        descriptive list.
      </para>
      <example id="ex.table">
        <title>A Typical Table</title>
        <informaltable>
          <tgroup cols="3">
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>File System</entry>
                <entry>File Size (Bytes)</entry>
                <entry>File System Size (Bytes)</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Ext2 or Ext3 (1 kB block size)</entry>
                <entry>2<superscript>34</superscript> (16 GB)</entry>
                <entry>2<superscript>41</superscript> (2 TB)</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Ext2 or Ext3 (2 kB block size)</entry>
                <entry>2<superscript>38</superscript> (256 GB)</entry>
                <entry>2<superscript>43</superscript> (8 TB)</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
      </example>
    </sect2>

  </sect1>