<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook45-profile.xsl"
                 type="text/xml" title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY copy "©">
<!ENTITY reg "®">
<!ENTITY tm "™">
<!ENTITY sm "℠">
]>

  <sect1 id="sec.language">
    <title>Language</title>

    <para>The following rules are intentionally kept concise.
      When in doubt about a style rule, refer to
      <citetitle>The Chicago Manual of Style</citetitle>, 15th
      Edition. When in doubt about the spelling or usage of a word, first refer
      to <xref linkend="app.terminology"/>. When the usage of a word is not
      regulated there, use American English spellings as defined on
      <ulink url="http://www.merriam-webster.com/"/>
      (<ulink url="http://www.m-w.com/"/> for short).
    </para>
    <para>If a product you are documenting is not listed in the terminology
      table, refer to the SUSE home page, <ulink url="http://www.suse.com"/>.
      If the product is not mentioned on the SUSE home page, refer to the
      Marketing department.
    </para>

    <sect2 id="sec.abbreviation">
      <title>Abbreviations</title>

      <para>Do not use any abbreviations, except <emphasis>etc.</emphasis> or
        abbreviations of common units of measurement. Do not create
        a plural of abbreviations by adding an <quote>s.</quote> Refer to
        <xref linkend="sec.number"/> for more information about units of
        measurement.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="sec.acronym">
      <title>Acronyms</title>
      <para>A title must not contain both an acronym and its expansion. When
        dealing with a term that is commonly written as an acronym, use the
        acronym in the title. When mentioning the term for the first time in
        the following text, use its expanded form. All following occurrences
        of the term in this chapter should then use the acronym.
      </para>
      <para>Sometimes chapters and parts are used across multiple
        documents, therefore provide the expansion of an acronym at
        least once per chapter. Be consistent in how you provide the
        expansion. If you use the acronym followed by the written out form
        in one chapter, do this in all other chapters too.
      </para>
      <para>Create plural forms of acronyms by adding a lowercase
        <quote>s,</quote> for example, <quote>CDs</quote> and
        <quote>BIOSs.</quote> Avoid using possessive forms of acronyms
        (a negative example would be <quote>XMLʼs specification</quote>)
        for reasons of clarity.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.capitalization">
      <title>Capitalization and Title Style</title>

      <para>In all running text, use sentence-style capitalization. That is,
        only capitalize the first word of a sentence and proper names.
      </para>
      <para>Use title-style capitalization for all types of headings and titles,
        including figure and table titles. This style is explained in
        <citetitle>The Chicago Manual of Style</citetitle> 8.167.
        A simplified version of these rules is below:
      </para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Capitalize the first and the last word.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Write articles in lowercase. Articles are: <emphasis>the</emphasis>,
            <emphasis>a</emphasis>, and <emphasis>an</emphasis>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Write prepositions in lowercase unless they are used with a verb
            (<quote>Logging In</quote>) or in a noun
            (<quote>The On Button</quote>). Prepositions are for example:
            <emphasis>up</emphasis>, <emphasis>in</emphasis>,
            <emphasis>of</emphasis>, <emphasis>through</emphasis>, and
            <emphasis>between</emphasis>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Write certain conjunctions in lowercase: <emphasis>and</emphasis>,
            <emphasis>but</emphasis>, <emphasis>for</emphasis>,
            <emphasis>nor</emphasis>, and <emphasis>or</emphasis>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Write <emphasis>as</emphasis> and <emphasis>to</emphasis> in
            lowercase.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Capitalize everything that is not mentioned above.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>In variable lists, capitalize the term in title style unless it
        is a complete sentence. In all list items, use sentence-style
        capitalization (capitalize the first letter and proper nouns only).
        Use title style for row and column labels in tables.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="sec.comma">
      <title>Commas</title>

      <para>Use commas between all items in a series of three or more elements.
        For example, write <quote>a, b,
        and c.</quote> Use commas around phrases like <emphasis>for
        example</emphasis> and <emphasis>that is</emphasis>. Introductory
        phrases at the beginning of a sentence are normally followed by a comma.
        For example, <quote>Before using YaST Online Update, configure
        a network connection.</quote>
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.contraction">
      <title>Contractions</title>

      <para>Do not use contractions, unless you are purposefully writing
        a casual document.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.dash">
      <title>Dashes</title>

      <para>Use en dashes (&ndash;) between numbers in a
        range in tables and figures.
      </para>
      <para>For punctuation, use em dashes (&mdash;).
        Do not surround em dashes with spaces. Use em dashes sparingly.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.end_sentence">
      <title>End of Sentence Punctuation</title>

      <para>End sentences in a period. Avoid using exclamation marks.
        Restrict question marks to question and answer sections.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.file_language">
      <title>File and Directory Names</title>

      <para>Under Linux, objects like directories, printers, or flash disks
        are all considered files. Therefore, the naming and markup
        conventions are the same for <quote>drives</quote> (for example,
        hard disks, CD-ROM drives, or flash disks), directories, or files.
      </para>
      <para>The layout for file names and directory names is the same. See the
       following example:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use forward slashes to separate nested directory or file
            names.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>When giving absolute paths, always start with a leading slash
            to indicate the root of the file system.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Do not use a trailing slash to distinguish between a file
            and a directory. Where differentiation is needed, provide it
            textually.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Most Linux file systems are case-sensitive. Use capitals exactly
        as they appear in the file system. For details on markup, refer to
        <xref linkend="sec.other_external"/> and
        <xref linkend="sec.file_markup"/>.
      </para>
      <para>When it is necessary to refer to file extensions, such as in
        compound words like <quote>PDF file</quote>, always capitalize the
        extension.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.bias">
      <title>Gender Bias</title>

      <para>Avoid indicating gender in your documentation. If possible,
        use plural to allow use of <quote>they</quote> as the pronoun.
        Otherwise, use <quote>he or she.</quote>
      </para>
      <para>For naming of example items, refer to <xref linkend="sec.name"/>.
        For more information on how to avoid gender bias, refer to
        <citetitle>The Chicago Manual of Style</citetitle> 5.43.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.heading">
      <title>Headings</title>
      <para>Keep headings short and simple. Do not use both an acronym and the
        written-out form in a heading. Make sure that headlines in a
        chapter follow the same pattern.
      </para>
      <para>Provide at least some introductory information between a heading
        and its subheadings.
      </para>
      <para>For advice on how to nest sections, refer to
        <xref linkend="sec.outline_level"/>.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.number">
      <title>Numbers and Measurements</title>

      <para>Write the integers zero through nine as words. Use numerals for all
        other numbers.
      </para>
      <para>When the unit of a measurement is abbreviated, always use
        numerals for the number. In measurements, add a non-breaking space
        (<sgmltag class="genentity">nbsp</sgmltag>)
        between the numeral and its corresponding unit abbreviation.
      </para>
      <para>
        For more information, refer to
        <citetitle>The Chicago Manual of Style</citetitle> 9.6.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.possessive">
      <title>Possessives</title>

      <para>Do not use possessives of acronyms and trademarked terms.
        Avoid possessives of inanimate objects.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.prefix">
      <title>Prefixes</title>

      <para>Add a hyphen after the prefix to prefixed words only if:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The last letter of the prefix and the first letter of the word
            are the same.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>You foresee misunderstandings. For example, there is a
            difference in meaning between <quote>recreate</quote> and
            <quote>re-create</quote>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.semicolon">
      <title>Semicolons</title>

      <para>Avoid using semicolons to join sentences. You may use semicolons
        in place of commas in very complicated series.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.slash">
      <title>Slashes</title>

      <para>Do not use slashes except when they are part of a standard
        technical term, such as <emphasis>TCP/IP</emphasis> or
        <emphasis>client/server</emphasis>.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.structure_sentence">
      <title>Sentence Structure</title>

      <para>Form clear and direct sentences with 20 words or less.
        Avoid complicated clauses. Make sure that the relationship between
        subject, verb, and object are clear. Avoid joining sentences with
        semicolons. Avoid ending sentences with prepositions.
      </para>
      <para>Avoid using parentheses. Where they are necessary, move them to
        the end of the sentence. Never nest parentheses.
      </para>
      <para>Always let the reader know the objective of an action before
        describing the action itself. As an example, write: <quote>To
        restore world peace, click <guimenu>Shake Hands</guimenu>.</quote>
        <remark>sknorr 2014-01-07: it's hard to take this quote seriously.
        Find something better.</remark>
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.tense">
      <title>Tense</title>
      <para>Use the simple present tense. Apply the simple present tense even
        to sentences with <quote>if</quote> or <quote>when</quote>
        clauses: <quote>If this happens, go there.</quote>
      </para>
      <para>Prerequisites of an action should be expressed in the present tense
        as well: <quote>Glibc is installed.</quote> In some cases, no
        verb is necessary before the prerequisite of an action:
        <quote>a 1&nbsp;GHz processor or better.</quote>
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.tone">
      <title>Tone and Voice</title>
      <para>Maintain a professional tone. Do not use contractions, except in
        casual documents. Do not use humor. Be honest and
        avoid absolutes and exaggerations, but focus on positive aspects.
      </para>
      <para>Use second person (<quote>you</quote>) to refer to the reader.
        Normally, the reader is the user or administrator that does
        the actions described. Do not overuse <quote>you.</quote> It
        is often understood, especially in directions.
      </para>
      <para>Where possible, use active voice. In active voice, the subject of
        the sentence performs the verb. For example, <quote>The root user
        performs administrative tasks</quote> is active voice.
        <quote>Administrative tasks are performed by the root user</quote>
        is passive voice.
      </para>
      <para>Use passive voice if there is no emphasis on the object of the verb
        or if the performer of the action is unknown. <quote>A SAMBA server
        must be configured in the network</quote> is an example of
        proper use of passive voice. The emphasis is on the server,
        not on the person configuring it.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.trademark">
      <title>Trademarks</title>

      <para>Most products referenced in the documentation are trademarked.
        Follow these rules when dealing with these terms:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Never use trademarks in headings.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Only use the marked version on the first occurrence of the
            product name in a chapter.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Only use the &reg;, &tm;, or &sm; marks for
            <phrase role="companyname">Attachmate</phrase> products.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use an * (asterisk) for all service marks or trademarks of
            third-party companies. This acknowledges the service mark
            or trademark of the other company. It also protects SUSE if the
            protection of the brand changes in any way.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>See <xref linkend="sec.product"/> for markup advice.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.ui_item_language">
      <title>User Interface Items</title>

      <para>When referring to labels of user interface items, do not include
        ending punctuation
        such as <literal>…</literal> or <literal>:</literal>. Whenever possible,
        refer to user interface item without identifying them as any special
        type of element. For example, use <quote>click
        <guimenu>OK</guimenu></quote> rather than <quote>click the
        <guimenu>OK</guimenu> button.</quote> However, complex dialogs may
        require more specific wording.
      </para>
      <para>For instructions concerning markup, refer to
        <xref linkend="sec.ui_item_markup"/>.
      </para>
    </sect2>

  </sect1>