<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook45-profile.xsl"
                 type="text/xml" title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY copy "©">
<!ENTITY reg "®">
<!ENTITY tm "™">
<!ENTITY sm "℠">
]>

<!-- Target audience: SUSE technical writers, OpenSUSE community technical
     writers, SUSE software developers -->

<article lang="en" id="art.styleguide">
  <title>SUSE Documentation Style Guide</title>
  <articleinfo>
    <releaseinfo>2014.01-beta</releaseinfo>
    <date><?dbtimestamp?></date>
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="authors.xml"/>
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
      href="legal_suse+gfdl.xml"/>
  </articleinfo>

  <abstract>
    <para>This guide provides answers to writing, style, and layout questions
      commonly arising when editing SUSE or openSUSE documentation. The
      <phrase role="productname">Novdoc</phrase>/
      <phrase role="productname">DocBook</phrase>
      markup reference at the end of this guide will help you
      choose the right XML element for your purpose. Following this guide will
      make your documentation more understandable and easier to translate.
    </para>
  </abstract>


  <sect1 id="sec.audience">
    <title>Audience</title>

    <para>Before starting to write, define the target audience of your
      documentation. Adjust tone, style, and technicality of the text based on
      the intended audience. Keep in mind that not all facts that seem
      obvious to you will be obvious to your readers. If you move parts of
      documents into other documents, make sure to adapt the parts you
      move to the new document.
    </para>
    <para>For later reference, document the defined target audience in the
      main file of every book and article. Place an XML comment directly
      before the relevant <sgmltag class="emptytag">book</sgmltag> or
      <sgmltag class="emptytag">article</sgmltag> element, such as this:
    </para>
    <screen>&lt;!-- Target audience: institutional desktop users. --&gt;</screen>
    <para>For more information about the usage of XML comments, see
      <xref linkend="sec.xmlcomment"/>. In many cases, there is no need to
      also add information about the target audience to the book or
      article text itself.
    </para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="sec.outline">
    <title>Outline of a Manual</title>

    <para>Maintain a consistent structure within your documents. The structure
      can vary between different books, articles or projects, but the most
      common type is documented here.
    </para>

    <sect2 id="sec.book">
      <title>Books</title>
      <para>You should always use a document structure that includes the
        following elements, in that order: a preface, and
        chapters which are split in sections. Optionally, add appendixes, a
        glossary, and an index. In some cases, parts can be created at the
        outline level above chapters.
      </para>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Title Page and Imprint</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Both title page and imprint are created automatically, but
              depend on information being present in the book.
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <formalpara>
                  <title>Title</title>
                  <para>Work with the marketing department to define the correct
                    book title. The book title should not contain the product
                    name and version.
                  </para>
                </formalpara>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <formalpara>
                  <title>Product Name and Product Version</title>
                  <para>Work with the marketing department to find the correct
                    product name and version number. Mark this information up
                    with <sgmltag class="emptytag">productname</sgmltag> and
                    <sgmltag class="emptytag">productnumber</sgmltag>,
                    respectively.
                  </para>
                </formalpara>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <formalpara>
                  <title>Documentation Version or Revision Information</title>
                  <para>Use the <sgmltag class="emptytag">releaseinfo</sgmltag>
                    element to mark up version or revision numbers of the
                    documentation itself. For further information
                    on how to enable SVN revision information in your document,
                    see
                      <ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/en/1.7/svn.advanced.props.special.keywords.html"/>.
                  </para>
                </formalpara>
              </listitem>
              <!-- sknorr, 2013-01-17: Not yet implemented. -->
              <!-- <listitem>
                <formalpara>
                  <title>Cover Image</title>
                  <para>Work with the marketing department to find a cover
                    image. Use the <sgmltag class="emptytag">cover</sgmltag>
                    element to include the image.
                  </para>
                </formalpara>
              </listitem> -->
              <listitem>
                <formalpara>
                  <title>Authorship Information</title>
                  <para>Create a separate file <filename>authors.xml</filename>
                    and add an <sgmltag class="emptytag">authorgroup</sgmltag>
                    listing all authors and contributors inside it. Include this
                    file with an XInclude.
                  </para>
                </formalpara>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <formalpara>
                  <title>Copyright Notice</title>
                  <para>Use the standard copyright notice reproduced below.
                    Change the starting year of the copyright protection to the
                    current year.
                  </para>
                </formalpara>
                <example>
                  <title>Standard Copyright Notice</title>
                  <screen>&lt;legalnotice&gt;
 &lt;para&gt;
  Copyright &amp;copy; <replaceable>[starting year]</replaceable>&amp;ndash;&lt;?dbtimestamp format="Y"?&gt;
  SUSE LLC and contributors. All rights reserved.
 &lt;/para&gt;
 &lt;para&gt;
  Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
  under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.2 or
  (at your option) version 1.3; with the Invariant Section being this
  copyright notice and license. A copy of the license version 1.2 is
  included in the section entitled &lt;quote&gt;GNU Free Documentation
  License&lt;/quote&gt;.
 &lt;/para&gt;
 &lt;para&gt;
  For &amp;suse; and Novell trademarks, see the Novell Trademark and
  Service Mark list at
  &lt;ulink url="http://www.novell.com/company/legal/trademarks/tmlist.html"/&gt;.
  All other third party trademarks are the property of their respective
  owners. A trademark symbol (&amp;reg;, &amp;trade; etc.) denotes a &amp;suse; or
  Novell trademark; an asterisk (*) denotes a third party trademark.
 &lt;/para&gt;
 &lt;para&gt;
  All information found in this book has been compiled with utmost
  attention to detail. However, this does not guarantee complete
  accuracy. Neither SUSE LLC, its affiliates, the authors nor the
  translators shall be held liable for possible errors or the
  consequences thereof.
 &lt;/para&gt;
&lt;/legalnotice&gt;</screen>
                </example>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Abstract</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Use an abstract to summarize the information provided in a
              book, article, or set in five or fewer sentences. Summarize the
              topic instead of summarizing the outline.
            </para>
            <example id="ex.abstract">
              <title>An Abstract</title>

              <para>SUSE Linux Enterprise ships with a number of different
                file systems, including Btrfs, Ext3, Ext4. Each file system
                has advantages and disadvantages that make it more or less
                suitable for a scenario. Professional high-performance
                setups can require a different choice of file system than
                a home user setup. This guide will help you choose the right
                one.
              </para>
            </example>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Table of Contents</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>The table of contents is generated automatically.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Preface</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>The preface of a book contains a brief overview of the content
              of a manual, related manuals, and typographical conventions. It
              may also contain information about its target audience.
          </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Parts</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>If you are writing a book with many chapters, create parts at
              the outline level above chapters. Parts should contain at least
              three chapters. Keep part titles
              clear and concise. Often a single noun is enough. Typical part
              titles include <emphasis>Installation</emphasis> or
              <emphasis>Network</emphasis>.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Chapters</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Chapters typically consist of the following elements (appendixes
              should be regarded an exception):
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <formalpara>
                  <title>Highlights</title>
                  <para>Use a highlights section to summarize the information
                    provided in a chapter in four or fewer bullet
                    points. Summarize the topic instead of summarizing the
                    outline.
                  </para>
                </formalpara>
                <example id="ex.highlights">
                  <title>A Highlights Section</title>
                  <para>This chapter will:</para>
                  <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Give you an overview over the file systems
                        available in
                        <phrase role="productname">SUSE Linux Enterprise</phrase>,
                        such as Ext3, Ext4, and Btrfs.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Inform you about their distinctive advantages and
                        disadvantages.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Help you choose the right one for your purpose.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </orderedlist>
                </example>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
              <formalpara>
                <title>Introductions</title>
                <para>Any introductory information follows directly after the
                  abstract and should not be placed in a separate section.
                </para>
              </formalpara>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <formalpara>
                  <title>Sections</title>
                  <para>Structure the detailed information, so users can skim
                    the text. Create sections for every major task, such as
                    installing, configuring, monitoring, and administering. If
                    helpful, split sections into subsections, but avoid going
                    above three levels of sections.
                  </para>
                </formalpara>
                <para>Sections start with an introductory paragraph outlining
                  the focus of the section. If the section describes a
                  sequential task, follow the introduction with a procedure
                  description, as discussed in <xref linkend="sec.procedure"/>.
                  Steps of a procedure can contain a cross reference
                  to a subsection where the necessary background is provided
                  and the action explained in more detail. See also:
                  <xref linkend="sec.crossreference"/>.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <formalpara>
                  <title>Troubleshooting</title>
                  <para>If you know of common mistakes or other problems a
                    user might encounter, list them in
                    a section named <emphasis>Troubleshooting</emphasis>.
                    Use the DocBook element
                    <sgmltag class="emptytag">qandaset</sgmltag>
                    (a Question and Answer section) to mark up
                    <emphasis>Troubleshooting</emphasis> problems.
                    In case you want to describe
                    solutions to more than ten problems, add topical subsections
                    (<sgmltag class="emptytag">qandadiv</sgmltag> elements)
                    below the <emphasis>Troubleshooting</emphasis> section.
                  </para>
                </formalpara>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <formalpara>
                  <title>For More Information</title>
                  <para>This section contains links to all sources of
                    information that might prove helpful in a given context.
                    Follow the general referencing guidelines in
                    <xref linkend="sec.crossreference"/> when creating such
                    sections.
                  </para>
                </formalpara>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Glossary</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>The optional glossary contains important terms in
              alphabetical order and provides a brief explanation.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.article">
      <title>Articles</title>

      <para>For articles, use a structure similar to that of books. However,
        that there is no equivalent of parts in articles. In articles,
        the function of chapters is filled by first-level sections
        (<sgmltag class="emptytag">sect1</sgmltag>).
      </para>
    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="sec.name">
      <title>Names of Example Items</title>

      <para>This section summarizes some conventions to use for creating
        generic names for objects that can occur in documentation. At least
        some of the following values should be provided through entities
        (see <xref linkend="sec.entity"/>).
      </para>

      <sect2 id="sec.domain">
        <title>Domains</title>

        <para>Use <ulink url="http://www.example.com"/> and
          <ulink url="http://www.example.org"/> as example domains. Both
          domains were registered for use in documentation.
        </para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec.host">
        <title>Host Names</title>

        <para>Use <systemitem>sun</systemitem> and
          <systemitem>earth</systemitem> or other planets of the solar system.
        </para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec.ipv4">
        <title>IPv4 Adresses</title>

        <para>Use addresses from the class C
          subnet <literal>255.255.255.0</literal> for examples. That is,
          replace the final <literal>0</literal> by any integer between
          <literal>0</literal> and <literal>255</literal>.
          To create examples using a larger setup, use
          addresses from the private network ranges. See
          <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Private_network"/>
          for more information.
        </para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec.ipv6">
        <title>IPv6 Adresses</title>

        <para>Use addresses from the subnet <literal>2001:0db8::/32</literal>
          for examples. That is, after the <literal>2001:0db8:</literal> prefix,
          add six four-digit numbers, each separated by a colon on both sides.
          Each of the hexadecimal digits may have a value between
          <literal>0</literal> and <literal>f</literal>. A valid example URL is
          <literal>2001:0db8:0123:4567:89ab:cdef:1234:5678</literal>. See
          <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IPv6_subnetting_reference"/>
          for more information.
        </para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec.user">
        <title>Users</title>

        <para>For example users, use free-software mascots, such as Tux (Linux
          kernel), Wilber (The GIMP), Geeko (SUSE), Foxkeh (Firefox), Konqi
          (KDE), or Duke (Java). In prompts, use the lowercase version of these
          names.
        </para>
      </sect2>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="sec.language">
    <title>Language</title>

    <para>The following rules are intentionally kept concise.
      When in doubt about a style rule, refer to
      <citetitle>The Chicago Manual of Style</citetitle>, 15th
      Edition. When in doubt about the spelling or usage of a word, first refer
      to <xref linkend="app.terminology"/>. When the usage of a word is not
      regulated there, use American English spellings as defined on
      <ulink url="http://www.merriam-webster.com/"/>
      (<ulink url="http://www.m-w.com/"/> for short).
    </para>
    <para>If a product you are documenting is not listed in the terminology
      table, refer to the SUSE home page, <ulink url="http://www.suse.com"/>.
      If the product is not mentioned on the SUSE home page, refer to the
      Marketing department.
    </para>

    <sect2 id="sec.abbreviation">
      <title>Abbreviations</title>

      <para>Do not use any abbreviations, except <emphasis>etc.</emphasis> or
        abbreviations of common units of measurement. Do not create
        a plural of abbreviations by adding an <quote>s.</quote> Refer to
        <xref linkend="sec.number"/> for more information about units of
        measurement.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="sec.acronym">
      <title>Acronyms</title>
      <para>A title must not contain both an acronym and its expansion. When
        dealing with a term that is commonly written as an acronym, use the
        acronym in the title. When mentioning the term for the first time in
        the following text, use its expanded form. All following occurrences
        of the term in this chapter should then use the acronym.
      </para>
      <para>Because sometimes chapters and parts are used across multiple
        documents, it is important to provide the expansion of an acronym at
        least once per chapter. Be consistent in how you provide the
        expansion. If you use the acronym followed by the written out form
        in one chapter, do this in all other chapters too.
      </para>
      <para>Create plural forms of acronyms by adding a lowercase
        <quote>s,</quote> for example, <quote>CDs</quote> and
        <quote>BIOSs.</quote> Avoid using possessive forms of acronyms
        (a negative example would be <quote>XMLʼs specification</quote>)
        for reasons of clarity.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.capitalization">
      <title>Capitalization and Title Style</title>

      <para>In all running text, use sentence-style capitalization, that is,
        only capitalize the first word of a sentence and proper names.
      </para>
      <para>Use title-style capitalization for all types of headings and titles,
        including figure and table titles. This style is explained in
        <citetitle>The Chicago Manual of Style</citetitle> 8.167.
        A simplified version of these rules is below:
      </para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Capitalize the first and the last word.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Lowercase articles, that is, <emphasis>the</emphasis>,
            <emphasis>a</emphasis>, and <emphasis>an</emphasis>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Lowercase prepositions, such as <emphasis>up</emphasis>,
            <emphasis>in</emphasis>, <emphasis>of</emphasis>,
            <emphasis>through</emphasis>, and <emphasis>between</emphasis>,
            unless they are used with a verb, such as <quote>Logging In</quote>
            or with a noun, as in <quote>The On Button</quote>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Lowercase the following conjunctions: <emphasis>and</emphasis>,
            <emphasis>but</emphasis>, <emphasis>for</emphasis>,
            <emphasis>nor</emphasis>, and <emphasis>or</emphasis>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Lowercase <emphasis>as</emphasis> and <emphasis>to</emphasis>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Capitalize everything that is not mentioned above.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>In variable lists, capitalize the term in title style unless it
        is a complete sentence. In all list items, use sentence-style
        capitalization (capitalize the first letter and proper nouns only).
        Use title style for row and column labels in tables.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="sec.comma">
      <title>Commas</title>

      <para>Use commas between all items in a series of three or more elements.
        For example, write <quote>a, b,
        and c.</quote> Use commas around phrases like <emphasis>for
        example</emphasis> and <emphasis>that is</emphasis>. Introductory
        phrases at the beginning of a sentence are normally followed by a comma.
        For example, <quote>Before using YaST Online Update, configure
        a network connection.</quote>
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.contraction">
      <title>Contractions</title>

      <para>Do not use contractions, unless you are purposefully writing
        a casual document.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.dash">
      <title>Dashes</title>

      <para>Use en dashes (<literal>&ndash;</literal>) between numbers in a
        range in tables and figures.
      </para>
      <para>For punctuation, use em dashes (<literal>&mdash;</literal>).
        Do not surround em dashes with spaces. Use em dashes sparingly.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.sentence.end">
      <title>End of Sentence Punctuation</title>

      <para>End sentences in a period. Avoid using exclamation marks.
        Restrict question marks to question and answer sections.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.file">
      <title>File and Directory Names</title>

      <para>Under Linux, objects like directories, printers, or flash drives
        are all considered files. Therefore, the naming and markup
        conventions are the same for <quote>drives</quote> (for example,
        hard drives, CD-ROM drives, or flash drives), directories, or files.
      </para>
      <para>The layout for file names and directory names is the same. See the
       following example:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use forward slashes to separate nested directory or file
            names.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>When giving absolute paths, always start with a leading slash
            to indicate the root of the file system.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Do not use a trailing slash to distinguish between a file
            and a directory. Where differentiation is needed, provide it
            textually.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Most Linux file systems are case-sensitive. Use capitals exactly
        as they appear in the file system. For details on markup, refer to
        <xref linkend="sec.otherexternal"/> and
        <xref linkend="sec.markup.inline.filenames_and_dirs"/>.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.bias">
      <title>Gender Bias</title>

      <para>Avoid indicating gender in your documentation. If possible,
        use plural to allow use of <quote>they</quote> as the pronoun.
        Otherwise, use <quote>he or she.</quote>
      </para>
      <para>For naming of example items, refer to <xref linkend="sec.name"/>.
        For more information on how to avoid gender bias, refer to
        <citetitle>The Chicago Manual of Style</citetitle> 5.43.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.number">
      <title>Numbers and Measurements</title>

      <para>Write integers zero through ten as words and use numerals for all
        others. For measurements, always use numerals when an abbreviation is
        used for the unit. Use a non-breaking
        (<sgmltag class="genentity">nbsp</sgmltag>)
        space between the numeral and corresponding unit abbreviation.
        For more information, refer to
        <citetitle>The Chicago Manual of Style</citetitle> 9.6.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.possessive">
      <title>Possessives</title>

      <para>Do not use possessives of acronyms and trademarked terms.
        Avoid possessives of inanimate objects.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.prefix">
      <title>Prefixes</title>

      <para>Do not add a hyphen after the prefix to prefixed words
        unless either the last letter of the prefix and the first letter of
        the word are the same or you foresee misunderstandings.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.semicolon">
      <title>Semicolons</title>

      <para>Avoid using semicolons to join sentences. You may use semicolons
        in place of commas in very complicated series.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.slash">
      <title>Slashes</title>

      <para>Do not use slashes except when they are part of a standard
        technical term, such as <emphasis>TCP/IP</emphasis> or
        <emphasis>client/server</emphasis>.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.sentence.structure">
      <title>Sentence Structure</title>

      <para>Form clear and direct sentences with 20 words or less.
        Avoid complicated clauses. Make sure that the relationship between
        subject, verb, and object are clear. Avoid joining sentences with
        semicolons. Avoid ending sentences with prepositions.
      </para>
      <para>Always let the reader know the objective of an action before
        describing the action itself. As an example, write: <quote>To
        restore world peace, click <guimenu>Shake Hands</guimenu>.</quote>
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.tense">
      <title>Tense</title>
      <para>Use the simple present tense. Apply the simple present tense even
        to sentences with <quote>if</quote> or <quote>when</quote>
        clauses: <quote>If this happens, go there.</quote>
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.tone">
      <title>Tone and Voice</title>
      <para>Maintain a professional tone. Do not use contractions, except in
        casual documents. Do not use humor. Be honest and
        avoid absolutes and exaggerations, but focus on positive aspects.
      </para>
      <para>Use second person (<quote>you</quote>) to refer to the reader.
        Normally, the reader is the user or administrator that does
        the actions described. Do not overuse <quote>you.</quote> It
        is often understood, especially in directions.
      </para>
      <para>Use active voice. Active voice means that the subject of the
        sentence performs the verb. For example, <quote>The root user
        performs administrative tasks</quote> is active voice.
        <quote>Administrative tasks are performed by the root user</quote>
        is passive voice. Passive voice can be used occasionally if
        there is a need to place emphasis on the object of the verb or
        if the performer of the action is unknown. <quote>A SAMBA server
        must be configured in the network</quote> is an example of
        proper use of passive voice. The emphasis is on the server,
        not on the person configuring it.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.uielement">
      <title>User Interface Elements</title>

      <para>When using labels of GUI elements, do not include ending punctuation
        like <literal>...</literal> or <literal>:</literal>. Whenever possible,
        refer to the elements without identifying them as a special type of
        dialog element. For example, use <quote>Click
        <guimenu>OK</guimenu></quote> rather than <quote>Click the
        <guimenu>OK</guimenu> button.</quote> However, some situations require
        a more specific wording, for example, if a dialog has many different
        graphical elements.
      </para>
      <para>For detailed instructions for the appropriate markup, especially
        concerning buttons, labels, and menu structures, refer to
        <xref linkend="sec.markup.inline.menus"/>.
      </para>
    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="sec.structure">
    <title>Structure and Markup</title>

    <para>Structure your documentation by tasks relevant to the user instead of
      providing reference documentation by describing each part of the user
      interface individually. In most cases, it is unnecessary to describe
      every minor functionality of a product. Describe what a product can do
      rather than its limitations.
    </para>

    <sect2 id="sec.admonition">
      <title>Admonitory and Advisory Paragraphs</title>

      <para>To make readers aware of potential problems and recent changes, or
        to give them tips, use an admonition element. Avoid using more than one
        admonition per page of PDF output.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title><sgmltag class="emptytag">warning</sgmltag></title>
            <para>Use these elements to warn of security issues, potential loss
              of data, damage to hardware, or physical hazards. Warnings must
              always precede the action to which they apply.
            </para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title><sgmltag class="emptytag">important</sgmltag></title>
            <para>Use these elements to give vital information.</para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title><sgmltag class="emptytag">tip</sgmltag></title>
            <para>Use these elements to introduce guidelines or give
              tips.
            </para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title><sgmltag class="emptytag">note</sgmltag></title>
            <para>Use these elements to highlight software version differences.
            </para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Follow these rules when writing admonitions:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Add a <sgmltag class="emptytag">title</sgmltag> to
            admonitions. In the title, state the subject of the admonition
            and, in the case of a <sgmltag class="emptytag">warning</sgmltag>,
            also the source of danger.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis><sgmltag class="emptytag">warning</sgmltag> or
            <sgmltag class="emptytag">important</sgmltag>:</emphasis>
            In the first paragraph, clearly state possible consequences
            of ignoring the danger.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis><sgmltag class="emptytag">warning</sgmltag> or
            <sgmltag class="emptytag">important</sgmltag>:</emphasis>
            In the second paragraph, explain how to
            avoid the danger. If there are multiple ways to avoid a danger,
            using a unordered list is helpful. In case multiple steps need
            to be taken to avoid a danger, use an ordered list or use a
            cross reference to refer to another part of the documentation.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <example>
        <title>An Example of a Warning</title>
        <screen>&lt;warning&gt;
  &lt;title&gt;Creating File Systems Can Take Several Hours&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;para&gt;Interrupting this process will result in a corrupt file system
    and an unusable installation.
  &lt;/para&gt;
  &lt;para&gt;Always wait until formatting has finished.&lt;/para&gt;
&lt;/warning&gt;</screen>
      </example>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.application">
      <title>Application Names</title>

      <para>When referring to an application, add a
          <sgmltag class="emptytag">phrase role="productname"</sgmltag> element
          around it. This will not result in a visual change but disables
          hyphenation:
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.callout">
      <title>Callouts</title>

      <para>Add the <sgmltag class="emptytag">co</sgmltag> elements directly
        after the part of a screen that you want to annotate. Do not try to
        align them above the part of a screen to annotate.
        Do not use more than ten callouts per example.
      </para>
      <example id="example.callout">
        <title>A Configuration File with Callouts</title>
        <screen>color white/blue black/light-gray <co id="col"/>
default 0 <co id="def"/>
timeout 8 <co id="time"/>
gfxmenu (hd0,0)/boot/message

title SUSE Linux Enterprise
    kernel (hd0,0)/boot/vmlinuz root=/dev/hda1 vga=0x31a selinux=0
    splash=silent resume=/dev/hda2 desktop elevator=as  showopts
    initrd (hd0,0)/boot/initrd

title Disk
    root (fd0)
    chainloader +1</screen>
        <calloutlist>
          <callout arearefs="col">
            <para>Color definitions to be used by the
              <phrase role="productname">GRUB</phrase> menu.
            </para>
          </callout>
          <callout arearefs="def">
            <para>Define the default option.</para>
          </callout>
          <callout arearefs="time">
            <para>Select a time-out after which booting starts automatically.
            </para>
          </callout>
        </calloutlist>
      </example>
      <para>For details on the markup of this element, refer to
        <xref linkend="sec.markup.block.callouts"/>.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.commandline">
      <title>Command Line Input and Output</title>

      <para>When dealing with user input and system output shorter than 30
        characters, format it with an inline element, such as
        <sgmltag class="emptytag">command</sgmltag> or
        <sgmltag class="emptytag">filename</sgmltag>. In all other cases,
        close the current paragraph and enclose it in a
        <sgmltag class="emptytag">screen</sgmltag> element.
      </para>

      <sect3 id="sec.command">
        <title>Commands</title>

        <screen>&lt;phrase role="productname"&gt;LibreOffice&lt;/phrase&gt; is an office suite.</screen>
        <para>Make sure to capitalize commands exactly as they are executed.
          Commands can be embedded in running text or
          presented as part of a screen environment. In running text,
          use <sgmltag class="emptytag">command</sgmltag> when referring
          to an actual command you would use on a command line:
        </para>
        <literallayout>Use <command>loffice</command> to start LibreOffice from the command line.</literallayout>
        <para>Nest options, surrounded by an
          <sgmltag class="emptytag">option</sgmltag> element,
          inside the command element. Options can also be used in
          text, separately from <sgmltag class="emptytag">command</sgmltag>. See
          <xref linkend="sec.markup.inline.commands"/>.
        </para>
        <para>Use markup for commands even inside
          <sgmltag class="emptytag">screen</sgmltag>
          environments.
        </para>
        <para>See also <xref linkend="sec.prompt"/>.
        </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="sec.placeholder">
        <title>Placeholders</title>

        <para>To mark up text that readers need to replace, use the
          <sgmltag class="emptytag">replaceable</sgmltag> element.
        </para>
            <screen>To list the contents of a directory, execute
&lt;command&gt;ls &lt;replaceable&gt;directory&lt;/replaceable&gt;&lt;/command&gt;.</screen>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="sec.variable">
        <title>Variable Names</title>

          <para>References to names of variables rather than to their value.
          </para>
          <screen>To select another display manager, start the YaST sysconfig editor
and change the value of &lt;variable&gt;DISPLAYMANAGER&lt;/variable&gt;.</screen>
      </sect3>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.crossreference">
      <title>Cross References</title>

      <para> Use the <sgmltag class="emptytag">xref</sgmltag> element (read:
        <quote>cross ref</quote>) when referring to an appendix, chapter,
        example, figure, part, preface, section, table, or question and answer
        set. The referenced element needs an
        <sgmltag class="attribute">id</sgmltag> attribute. When
        referencing these elements, do not insert a text label like
        <quote>appendix</quote>, <quote>chapter</quote>, <quote>part</quote>,
        <quote>preface</quote>, <quote>section</quote>, <quote>table</quote>,
        <quote>figure</quote>, and <quote>example</quote>. These are inserted
        automatically.
      </para>
      <para>Do not insert references to single paragraphs
        (<sgmltag class="emptytag">para</sgmltag>). If you need to reference
        a list, insert <sgmltag class="emptytag">id</sgmltag> and
        <sgmltag class="emptytag">xreflabel</sgmltag>.
      </para>
      <para>Other types of references to resources are described in
        <xref linkend="sec.otherexternal"/> and
        <xref linkend="sec.link"/>.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.link">
      <title>External Links</title>

      <para>Where possible, collect links in a
        <quote>For More Information</quote> section at the end of the chapter.
        This will help users focus on your documentation instead of leading
        them to other resources before they had a chance to read the end
        of the sentence.
      </para>
      <para>To mark up multiple links, create an
        <sgmltag class="emptytag">itemizedlist</sgmltag> around
        them. Do not use a list environment for only one link.
        If you need to present a large number of links, group them by topic and
        create a separate list environment for each group. Provide a
        comprehensive title for each of the groups or an introductory sentence.
      </para>
      <para>Use the <sgmltag class="emptytag">ulink</sgmltag> element to mark up
        URLs that can be opened with a web browser, such as
        <ulink url="http://www.suse.de"/>.
        Always add the correct protocol prefix (for example,
        <literal>http://</literal>),
        otherwise links will not work. Never use <sgmltag>filename</sgmltag>
        for a link, as that would both disable the link checker and make the
        link unclickable. Avoid entering a text label between the
        <sgmltag class="emptytag">ulink</sgmltag> start and end tags.
      </para>
      <para>Try to make URLs as short as possible before pasting them into your
        documentation. Many long URLs can be shortened by leaving away
        non-essential pieces of them. This is often the case with search URLs
        or URLs of Internet news media. If a web site provides a built-in URL
        shortener, use that. Do not resort to using external URL shorteners, as
        that both hides the actual destination a link will take the user to and
        introduces an extra element of uncertainty, as the shortening service
        may disappear or become unreliable in the future.
      </para>
      <para>Do not use <sgmltag class="emptytag">ulink</sgmltag> to link to SUSE
        documentation outside of the current document set. Instead, use the
        appropriate entity for the book title. Always reference the book
        itself, as chapter names can change.
      </para>
      <para>Where possible, provide translators with localized versions of
        links in the comments of the source file.
      </para>
      <para>Other types of references to resources are described in
        <xref linkend="sec.crossreference"/> and
        <xref linkend="sec.otherexternal"/>.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.example">
      <title>Examples</title>

      <para>Use examples to illustrate complex processes. Avoid adding
        paragraphs of text to examples.
        Many of the rules established in <xref linkend="sec.graphic"/> also
        apply to examples.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Examples are used to present long commands, commands
            together with their output, lines of code, configuration files,
            excerpts of configuration files, and output, such as system
            messages.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Never indent text inside
            <sgmltag class="emptytag">screen</sgmltag>
            elements as you do in other XML elements. All whitespace inside
            <sgmltag class="emptytag">screen</sgmltag> elements shows up
            verbatim.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Only use examples where they are necessary for understanding
            the documentation.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Always give examples a title and an ID.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <example id="ex.ex.call">
        <title>Calling ps to Get Process Information</title>
        <screen><prompt>tux &gt; </prompt><command>ps <option>-xa</option></command>

5170 ?        S      0:00 kdeinit: khotkeys
5172 ?        S      0:02 kdeinit: kdesktop
5174 ?        S      0:04 kdeinit: kicker
5177 ?        S      0:00 kdeinit: kpowersave
5179 ?        S      0:00 kdeinit: klipper</screen>
      </example>
      <para>For details on displaying computer input and output, refer to
        <xref linkend="sec.commandline"/>.
        For details on markup, refer to
        <xref linkend="sec.markup.block.examples"/>.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.glossary">
      <title>Glossaries</title>
      <para>An optional glossary contains terms and their definitions. Make sure
        that the glossary entries are appropriate to the intended audience. Define
        unfamiliar terms and specialized jargon.
      </para>
      <para>Define infinitive forms of verbs and singular nouns. Use lowercase for
        the term unless it is a proper noun.
      </para>
      <para>Use cross-references to link acronyms with their written out forms.
        Define the written out form. Use a <emphasis>See</emphasis> reference for
        the acronym form to link it to the defined written out form.
      </para>
      <para>The markup for a glossary entry is shown in
        <xref linkend="ex.glossary"/>.
      </para>
      <example id="ex.glossary">
        <title>A Typical Example of a Glossary</title>
        <screen>&lt;glossary&gt;
 &lt;title&gt;Glossary&lt;/title&gt;
 &lt;glossdiv&gt;
  &lt;title&gt;D&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;glossentry&gt;
   &lt;glossterm&gt;DocBook&lt;/glossterm&gt;
   &lt;glossdef&gt;
    &lt;para&gt;
     DocBook provides a system for writing structured documents
     using SGML or XML. It is particularly well-suited to books
     and papers about computer hardware and software, though it
     is by no means limited to them.
    &lt;/para&gt;
   &lt;/glossdef&gt;
  &lt;/glossentry&gt;
 &lt;/glossdiv&gt;
&lt;/glossary&gt;</screen>
      </example>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.graphic">
      <title>Graphics and Figures</title>
      <para>Where they are helpful for following the explanation, use
        screenshots and graphics. If you intend to use screenshots in a
        document, consider the following issues first:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>A screenshot should illustrate a complex situation in which
            the user cannot easily follow the text otherwise.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Only illustrate steps where user meaningful user interactions
            are necessary. Do not create screenshots of progress bars or
            confirmation windows.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Choose only those screenshots that show the most important
            dialogs or choices during the whole process is sufficient.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>If you intend to use graphics in documentation, think of the
        following issues first:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>KISS (<quote>keep it short and simple</quote>). Graphics
            should always simplify complex issues and not confuse the reader
            by their complexity. Embedding text in graphic adds to complexity.
            Use as little text as possible. Be aware that some languages use
            up to twice as much space for a given phrase than English.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Reference the figure from the text by means of an
            <sgmltag class="emptytag">xref</sgmltag>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.heading">
      <title>Headings</title>
      <para>Each level of heading should have two or more headings. Lonely
        subheadings are not allowed. Make headings in a group parallel by using
        a similar structure for the wording.
      </para>
      <para>Keep headings short and simple. Do not use both an acronym and the
        written-out form in a heading.
      </para>
      <para>Provide content between a heading and its subheadings. In some
        cases, this is only a small paragraph of introductory information.
        In other cases, more information can be provided.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.index">
      <title>Indexes</title>
      <para>Insert index terms as close to the relevant text as possible.
        When more than five paragraphs belong to a topic, use a page range.
        Nest index terms up to two levels deep.
      </para>
      <para>When indexing, look for information a user is likely to be trying to
        find. Adapt breadth and depth of included index terms for a given
        topic to the weight it has within the manual. Never index
        <quote>For More Information</quote> sections, abstracts,
        or commands that only appear as means to a different end.
      </para>
      <para>Be consistent in the terms you index. However,
        consider that users might not have the exact same terms in mind as you
        do, especially when it comes to highly technical words or brands.
        Write nouns in the plural. Write verbs in a gerund form
        (<emphasis>-ing</emphasis>). Use sentence-style capitalization for
        index terms.
      </para>
      <para>If an entry has six or more page references, try to subsume them
        as subentries under a single entry. If an entry has only a single
        subentry, consider deleting the subentry.
      </para>
      <para>Check for inconsistencies that result in multiple items in
        the index. Check all <emphasis>see</emphasis> and
        <emphasis>see also</emphasis> references for consistency.
        Items should not have both a page and a
        <emphasis>see</emphasis> reference. Where possible, avoid using page
        references and <emphasis>see also</emphasis> together.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.list">
      <title>Lists</title>

      <para>SUSE and openSUSE documentation uses the following types of lists
        (the respective XML elements are given in parentheses):
      </para>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Bullet Lists (<sgmltag class="emptytag">itemizedlist</sgmltag>)
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>See
              <ulink url="http://www.docbook.org/tdg/en/html/itemizedlist.html"/>
              for details of markup.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Numbered Lists (<sgmltag class="emptytag">orderedlist</sgmltag>)
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>See
              <ulink url="http://www.docbook.org/tdg/en/html/orderedlist.html"/>
              for details of markup.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Descriptive Lists
            (<sgmltag class="emptytag">variablelist</sgmltag>)
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>See
              <ulink url="http://www.docbook.org/tdg/en/html/variablelist.html"/>
              for details on markup.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      <para>Consider the following general rules when creating or editing list
        environments:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>List environments should be used cautiously. Their markup is
            quite distinct and overusing them might disrupt the text flow.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Always introduce a list in the text. If needed for reference or
            better coordination with the related text, add an optional title
            and an <sgmltag class="attribute">id</sgmltag> attribute.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>A list must contain at least two items. If items are short
            and simple in structure, consider incorporating them in the
            flowing text instead of creating a list environment.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use sentence-style capitalization for the list items. Use
            title-style capitalization for terms in descriptive lists.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>When using multiple sentences as a list item, end all items
            in that list with a period.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Make sure that the items are grammatically parallel
            constructions providing a pattern that makes it easier
            to follow the text.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Never nest more than three lists within each other. In such cases,
        try to restructure the information using a combination of
        lists and running texts.
      </para>

      <sect3 id="sec.bullet">
        <title>Bullet Lists</title>

        <para>Bullet lists are often used to provide an overview of information
          or to introduce or summarize information. They should be used when
          the order of list items is irrelevant.
        </para>
        <para>If needed, assign an <sgmltag class="attribute">id</sgmltag>
          attribute to an itemized list and add a title to reference it.
          Individual list items may be referenced by assigning an
          <sgmltag class="attribute">id</sgmltag> and an
          <sgmltag class="attribute">xreflabel</sgmltag> attribute. The entry is
          then identified by the value of
          <sgmltag class="attribute">id</sgmltag>
          and the value of <sgmltag class="attribute">xreflabel</sgmltag> is
          printed as the label of this item. See
          <xref linkend="sec.crossreference"/> and
          <xref linkend="sec.markup.inline.referencing"/> for detailed
          information.
        </para>
        <example id="ex.bulllist">
          <title>A Bullet List</title>
          <para>The following operating systems are supported:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Windows 2000 and newer</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Linux, kernel 2.4 and newer</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>FreeBSD 7 and newer</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </example>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="sec.numbered">
        <title>Numbered Lists</title>

        <para>Use numbered lists when items have a strict order, hierarchy, or
          importance. If order is not relevant, use a bullet list or a
          descriptive list. Do not use numbered lists to describe procedures.
          Complex sequential actions are better described by means of the
          procedure environment (see <xref linkend="sec.procedure"/>
          for a detailed description).
        </para>
        <para>If needed, assign an <sgmltag class="attribute">id</sgmltag>
          attribute to a numbered list and add a title to it in order to
          reference it. Individual list items may be referenced by assigning an
          <sgmltag class="attribute">id</sgmltag> and
          <sgmltag class="attribute">xreflabel</sgmltag> attribute. The
          entry is then identified by the value of
          <sgmltag class="attribute">id</sgmltag> and the value of
          <sgmltag class="attribute">xreflabel</sgmltag> is printed as the label
          of this item. See <xref linkend="sec.crossreference"/> and
          <xref linkend="sec.markup.inline.referencing"/> for detailed
          information.
        </para>
        <example id="ex.numlist">
          <title>A Numbered List</title>
          <para>Make sure the following requirements are met before trying to
            set up an Apache Web server:
          </para>
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>The network connection of the machine is configured
                properly.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>The exact system time of the machine is maintained by
                synchronizing with a time server. This is necessary because
                parts of the HTTP protocol depend on the correct time.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>The latest security updates are installed. If in doubt,
                run an online update.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>The default Web server port (port 80) is opened in the
                firewall. For this, configure the SUSEFirewall2 to allow the
                service <guimenu>HTTP Server</guimenu> in the external zone.
                This can be done using YaST.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </example>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="sec.descriptive">
        <title>Descriptive Lists</title>

        <para>Use descriptive lists when defining terms or describing options.
          Each item of a descriptive list contains a short term that is then
          further explained by means of an explanatory paragraph.
        </para>
        <para>Use title-style capitalization for the term. Use sentence-style
          for the list item.
        </para>
        <para>You may assign an <sgmltag class="attribute">id</sgmltag>
          attribute to the list and add a title to it in order to reference it.
          Individual list items may be referenced by assigning an
          <sgmltag class="attribute">id</sgmltag>. The entry is then identified
          by the value of <sgmltag class="attribute">id</sgmltag> and
          referenced by the term.
        </para>
        <example id="ex.varlist">
          <title>A Descriptive List</title>
          <para>This book consists of several parts:</para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Installation</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>Learn about the installation and initial configuration
                  of a Linux system.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>System</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>Get a basic understanding of the system components.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </example>
      </sect3>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.keyboard">
      <title>Keys and Key Combinations</title>

      <para>Capitalize all keys as printed on a standard keyboard. Following
        this rule, capitalize all letter keys. If you need to refer to a
        capitalized character, use
        <keycombo><keycap function="shift"/><keycap>Z</keycap></keycombo>,
        for example. Introduce this convention by means of the
        <quote>Typographical Conventions</quote> section of the introduction.
      </para>
      <para>Localization of the identifiers for both modifiers and
        special keys can be handled by DocBook itself, if you use the
        <sgmltag class="emptytag">keycap</sgmltag> element and an appropriate
        <literal>function</literal> value. For details, refer to
        <xref linkend="sec.markup.inline.keys"/>.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.otherexternal">
      <title>References to Other External Resources</title>

      <para>References to man pages and info pages should generally be
        made in the format <quote>the man page of
        <command>command</command></quote> or
        <quote>the info page of <command>command</command></quote>. In a
        situation where the category of the page is needed, add
        for example <quote>(<command>man 9 command</command>)</quote>
        to the end.
      </para>
      <para>To reference file names, use the
        <sgmltag class="emptytag">filename</sgmltag>
        element. To reference e-mail addresses, use the
        <sgmltag class="emptytag">email</sgmltag>
        element. In either case, do not include a protocol prefix, that is
        <literal>file://</literal> or <literal>mailto:</literal>, respectively.
      </para>
      <para>Insert references to external (not SUSE or openSUSE) physical
        books in the format <quote>Title by Author (ISBN #00000000).</quote>
        Inclusion of the ISBN is optional. Place the title in a
        <sgmltag class="emptytag">citetitle</sgmltag> element. For example:
      </para>
      <screen>&lt;citetitle&gt;Indexing Books&lt;/citetitle&gt; by Nancy C. Mulvany
(ISBN 0-226-55014-1) is a useful guide to indexing.</screen>
      <para>It is useful to provide language-specific references in the
        translated books. If the authors know of language-specific versions,
        they can include them in comments for translators. As time permits,
        translators should look for corresponding language-specific resources.
        For URLs, provide only the language-specific version of a site. Use the
        English as a fall-back. For books, provide the title of the translated
        version along with the original title if such a translation exists.
      </para>
      <para>Other types of references to resources are described in
        <xref linkend="sec.crossreference"/> and
        <xref linkend="sec.link"/>.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.procedure">
    <title>Procedures</title>

      <para>Use procedures to describe sequential tasks. A procedure
        consists of the following elements:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>A title and an <sgmltag class="attribute">id</sgmltag>
            attribute.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>An introductory phrase establishing the purpose of the
            procedure. If the procedure is otherwise the only element in
            its section, place the introductory phrase before the procedure.
            If necessary, add any preconditions of the operation after the
            introductory phrase.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Short, simple steps and substeps describing the actions to
            be performed. See also <xref linkend="sec.sentence.structure"/>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Describe alternative actions inside a substep element
        containing steps linked by <quote>or.</quote> Apply
        <sgmltag class="attribute">performance=optional</sgmltag>
        attribute optional steps.
      </para>
      <para>Steps may contain a link to an explanatory
        subsection providing further details on the step.
      </para>
      <procedure id="pro.useradd">
        <title>Adding Users with YaST</title>
        <para>To add a new user to the system, perform the following steps:
        </para>
        <step>
          <para>Open <guimenu>YaST</guimenu></para>
        </step>
        <step performance="optional">
          <para>If you are asked, type the password of the
            <systemitem>root</systemitem> user and click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
          </para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>Click <guimenu>User and Group Management</guimenu>.</para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>To open the <guimenu>Add a New User</guimenu> dialog, click
            <guimenu>Add</guimenu>.
          </para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>Type in the user data and click <guimenu>Create</guimenu>.
          </para>
        </step>
        <step performance="optional">
          <para>Repeat from the third step to add more
            users.
          </para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>Leave the YaST module by clicking <guimenu>OK</guimenu>.
          </para>
        </step>
      </procedure>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.product">
      <title>Products and Trademarks</title>

      <para>Always use the preferred product name instead of, for instance, an
        acronym. When referring to a product, add a
        <sgmltag class="emptytag">phrase role="productname"</sgmltag> element
        around it.
        This will not result in a visual change but disables hyphenation:
      </para>
      <screen>&lt;phrase role="productname"&gt;LibreOffice&lt;/phrase&gt; is an office suite.</screen>
      <para>Most products referenced in the documentation are trademarked.
        Follow these rules when dealing with these terms:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Never use trademarks in headings.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Only use the marked version on the first occurrence of the
            product name in a chapter.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Only use the &reg;, &tm;, or &sm; marks for
            <phrase role="companyname">Attachmate</phrase> products.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use an * (asterisk) for all service marks or trademarks of
            third-party companies. This both acknowledges the service mark
            or trademark of the other company and protects SUSE in case the
            protection of the brand changes in any way.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.prompt">
      <title>Prompts</title>

      <para>When documenting commands entered into Bash with a
        <sgmltag class="emptytag">screen</sgmltag> element, always prefix them
        with a prompt marked up this way:
      </para>
      <screen>&lt;prompt&gt;tux &amp;gt; &lt;/prompt&gt;&lt;command&gt;ls&lt;/command&gt;</screen>
      <para>Never include a host name or path in your prompts to avoid making
        them longer than necessary. The first restricted user should always use
        the name <emphasis>tux</emphasis>. For other names of restricted users,
        see <xref linkend="sec.bias"/>.
      </para>
      <para>Avoid using root prompts in your documentation by using the
        <command>sudo</command> where applicable. If you do need a root prompt,
        always mark it up as following:
      </para>
      <screen>&lt;prompt&gt;root # &lt;/prompt&gt;&lt;command&gt;yast&lt;/command&gt;</screen>
      <para>When documenting prompts other than the one of Bash, use a
        custom prompt that is as generic as possible.
      </para>
      <para>For consistency, it is helpful to create entities for the prompts
        used in your documentation. To learn more, refer to
        <xref linkend="sec.entity"/>.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.table">
      <title>Tables</title>

      <para>Use tables to present large numbers of similar facts. Tables are
        easy to scan and compare. Always keep tables simple enough to not
        require long explanations even for readers unfamiliar with the topic.
      </para>
      <para>A table always has a title and should have an
        <sgmltag class="attribute">id</sgmltag> attribute.
      </para>
      <para>Value and description pairs are better handled by means of a
        descriptive list.
      </para>
      <example id="ex.tab">
        <title>A Typical Table</title>
        <informaltable id="tab.maxsize">
          <tgroup cols="3">
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>File System</entry>
                <entry>File Size (Bytes)</entry>
                <entry>File System Size (Bytes)</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Ext2 or Ext3 (1 kB block size)</entry>
                <entry>2<superscript>34</superscript> (16 GB)</entry>
                <entry>2<superscript>41</superscript> (2 TB)</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Ext2 or Ext3 (2 kB block size)</entry>
                <entry>2<superscript>38</superscript> (256 GB)</entry>
                <entry>2<superscript>43</superscript> (8 TB)</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
      </example>
    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="sec.manage">
    <title>Managing Documents</title>

    <sect2 id="sec.remark">
      <title>Remarks</title>
      <para>Use remarks for editorial comments. Remarks can be placed within,
        before, or after a para but must always be within a section element.
        When creating output, remarks can be made visible and thus help the
        editorial process.
      </para>
      <para>Start remarks with your user name and the current date, then add
        a colon (<literal>:</literal>) and finally your actual remark.
        To comment on someone else's remark, add a new remark directly below it.
        Delete remarks when the corresponding issue is resolved.
      </para>
      <screen>&lt;remark&gt;tux (2013-10-13): could not find the option for foo&lt;/remark&gt;
&lt;remark&gt;geeko (2013-11-02): see /usr/share/doc/foo.html&lt;/remark&gt;</screen>
      <para>You can add a <sgmltag class="attribute">role</sgmltag> attribute
        with one of the following values to show the type of the remark:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title><sgmltag class="attvalue">structure</sgmltag></title>
              <para>Use this type of remark to suggest changes to the text
                or XML structure.
              </para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title><sgmltag class="attvalue">language</sgmltag></title>
              <para>Use this type of remark to suggest language improvements.
              </para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title><sgmltag class="attvalue">needinfo</sgmltag></title>
              <para>Use this type of remark to mark sections where you need
                input from others, such as developers.
              </para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title><sgmltag class="attvalue">trans</sgmltag></title>
              <para>Use this type of remark give hints to translators.</para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.xmlcomment">
      <title>XML Comments</title>

      <para>XML comments can be used for temporarily disabling portions of
        text. Another use of XML comments is to create more permanent internal
        comments or to mark up changes made for layout reasons.
      </para>
      <tip>
        <title>Creating Valid Comments</title>
        <para>Do not use <literal>--</literal> in comments.
          <literal>--</literal> is the first part of end-of-comment string
          <literal>--&gt;</literal> and thus causes validation to fail.
        </para>
      </tip>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec.entity">
      <title>Entities</title>

      <para>Entities are used to expand text. There are several situations in
        which they can be used:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Representation of special characters that cannot easily
            be displayed, entered or memorized.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Integration of external files by entities representing
            references to their file names.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Text expansion for repeating content.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Once an entity is defined, it can be used in many places. Entities
        reduce the risk of translation errors and increase consistency because
        they are translated once and automatically expanded elsewhere.
      </para>

      <sect3 id="sec.entity.handling">
        <title>Using Entity Files</title>

        <para>SUSE uses a small set of custom entities. This set is localized
          for each supported language. Find the SUSE set of entities in the file
          <filename>entity-decl.ent</filename> under each documentation project
          and each language. When the set has been modified for a new product
          release, this file must be updated in the supported languages as well.
        </para>
        <para>Each header of a SUSE XML file includes the entity declaration
          file (by means of an entity):
        </para>
        <screen>&lt;!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../entity-decl.ent"&gt;
%entities;</screen>
        <example id="ex.entity">
          <title>Excerpt from a SUSE entity-decl.ent</title>
          <screen>&lt;!ENTITY<co id="co.decl"/> exampleserver<co id="co.def"/>   "sun<co id="co.val"/>"&gt;
&lt;!ENTITY exampleserverip    "&amp;exampledomainip;.20"&gt;
&lt;!ENTITY exampleserverfq    "&amp;exampleserver;.&amp;exampledomain;"<co id="co.ent"/>&gt;</screen>
          <calloutlist>
            <callout arearefs="co.decl">
              <para>The kind of declaration to be made.</para>
            </callout>
            <callout arearefs="co.def">
              <para>Defines the entity name.</para>
            </callout>
            <callout arearefs="co.val">
              <para>Sets the value to which the processed entity should
                be expanded.
              </para>
            </callout>
            <callout arearefs="co.ent">
              <para>Nests an entity in the value.</para>
            </callout>
          </calloutlist>
        </example>
        <para>A few hints for working with entities in SUSE documentation
          projects:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>If there should be any need for defining special entities
              (for example, for localization purposes), add the new
              definitions to the appropriate
              <filename>entity-decl.ent</filename> file. Never include
              these definitions in the file header.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>When translating entities, translate the value, but never
              change the entity name (see <xref linkend="ex.entity"/>).
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Always use the exact notation of the entities when
              translating files to avoid processing errors.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Make sure that you use proper UTF-8 encoding when editing and
              saving the entity declaration file or any of the SUSE XML files.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="sec.entity.expansion">
        <title>Common Types of Entities</title>

        <para>The following provides some background on the most important
          entities used in creating documentation for SUSE products. To be able
          to adjust product names of platform branding even past any deadlines,
          a set of entities must represent the frequently-changing product names.
          The same applies to book titles. An
          <filename>entity-decl.ent</filename>
          file contains several different categories of entities. These are:
        </para>
        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>General Entities</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>These feature mostly network IP addresses, host names, and
                user names.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Books</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>If possible, any book created by our team has a title entity
                in case sudden changes are necessary.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Platforms</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>To avoid touching our content whenever a hardware vendor
                rebrands its products, we use entities for all hardware
                architectures referenced in the books.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Products</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>We maintain a list of entities of all SUSE-based product
                names and some other products and applications for which we
                write documentation.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
        <para>There are several guidelines to consider when working with product
          entities for SUSE documentation:
        </para>
        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Entity Selection</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Use the entity name
                <sgmltag class="genentity">product</sgmltag> to
                identify the product for which the documentation is built. Set the
                value of this entity is set once per release and let it
                expand to the name of the current product.
              </para>
              <screen>&lt;phrase role="productname"&gt;&amp;product;&lt;/phrase&gt; includes openLDAP.</screen>
              <para>If you need to reference a particular product, use a more
                specific entity.
              </para>
              <screen>The ext2 file system has been included in the &lt;literal&gt;&amp;suse;&lt;/literal&gt;
kernel since &lt;literal&gt;&amp;suselinux;&lt;/literal&gt; XYZ.</screen>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Acronyms</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Avoid using acronyms of product names where they are not
                the preferred form of the name. If you do define an
                additional acronym version of a longer product name, append
                an <literal>a</literal> to the end of the entity name, such
                as in <sgmltag class="genentity">slesa</sgmltag>.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Trademarks</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Follow the rules under <xref linkend="sec.product"/>.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="docu_styleguide.terminology.xml"/>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="docu_styleguide.markup.xml"/>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="gfdl.xml"/>
</article>
