<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<sect1 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="sec-techwriting">
 <title>Writing technical documentation</title>

 <para>
  Technical writing has certain characteristics that make it different from
  other types of writing. Its objective is to provide readers with complex
  information and comprehensive answers they are searching for. The content
  should be well-structured, clear, and concise. Effective technical
  documentation is straightforward, detailed and focused on problem-solving,
  and there is a specific workflow for its creation:
 </para>

 <variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Defining the target audience</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Adjust tone, style, and technicality of the text based on the intended
     audience. Keep in mind that not all facts that seem obvious to you will be
     obvious to your readers.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Researching a topic</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Start with research on the information that is relevant to the target
     audience. Receive essential input from issue tracking systems like GitHub,
     and project management tools.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Writing about a topic</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Start writing at an early stage, even if you have not finished your
     research yet. Prepare a draft document and discuss it with subject-matter
     experts.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>Getting reviews</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     In a first review of your text, identify and fix the most obvious issues
     like typos, unfinished sentences, etc. After self-review, ask for a
     technical review by dedicated specialists. A technical review uncovers
     technical or factual errors like missing or misspelled package names,
     wrong commands, or forgotten options.
    </para>
    <para>
     Request a peer review which can improve your text and detect any
     structural problems or logical traps. You can then do a spell check, link
     check, and style check with the DAPS tool.
    </para>
    <para>
     Finally, ask for a linguistic review that tackles language issues, typos,
     inconsistencies, and style guide compliance.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
 </variablelist>
 <para>
  <!--  For more information on how to produce meaningful content that will rank high
  on the Web, see Section ???, “Writing for the Web”, and Section ???,
  “Writing SEO-friendly content”.-->
 </para>
 </sect1>
