<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<sect1 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="sec-language">
 <title>Language</title>

 <para>
  The following rules are intentionally kept concise. When in doubt about a
  style rule, see <citetitle>The Chicago Manual of Style</citetitle>,
  15th Edition. When in doubt about the spelling or usage of a word, first
  see <xref linkend="app-terminology"/>. When the usage of a word is
  not regulated there, use American English spellings as defined on
  <link xlink:href="https://www.merriam-webster.com/"/>
  (<link xlink:href="https://www.m-w.com/"/> for short).
 </para>

 <para>
  If a product you are documenting is not listed in the terminology table,
  refer to the &suse; home page, <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com"/>. If
  the product is not mentioned on the &suse; home page, refer to the Marketing
  department.
 </para>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec-abbreviation">
  <title>Abbreviations</title>
  <para>
   Where possible, avoid using abbreviations. Especially avoid unusual
   abbreviations. You may create plurals of acronyms. In all other cases,
   avoid creating plurals of abbreviations.
  </para>
  <sect3 xml:id="sec-acronym">
   <title>Acronyms</title>
   <para>
    Introduce acronyms by providing the expansion in parentheses after the
    acronym.
    Sometimes chapters and parts are used across multiple documents.
    Therefore, provide the expansion of an acronym at least once per chapter.
   </para>
   <para>
    However, do not use headlines to introduce an acronym. Headlines or captions
    must not contain both an acronym and its
    expansion. If a term is commonly written as an
    acronym, use the acronym in the title. When mentioning the term for the
    first time in the following text, use its expanded form. All following
    occurrences of the term in this chapter should then use the acronym.
   </para>
   <para>
    Create plural forms of acronyms by adding a lowercase <quote>s,</quote>.
    For example, use <quote>CDs</quote> and <quote>BIOSes.</quote> Never add
    an apostrophe before the <quote>s</quote> or <quote>es.</quote>
   </para>
   <para>
    For clarity, avoid using possessive forms of acronyms. For example, do not
    use <quote>XMLʼs specification</quote>.
   </para>
  </sect3>
  <sect3 xml:id="sec-latin">
   <title>Latin abbreviations</title>
   <para>
    Do not use Latin abbreviations. Use the full English form: for example,
    use <quote>that is</quote> instead of <quote>i.e.</quote>. As an
    exception to this rule, the abbreviation <emphasis>etc.</emphasis> is
    allowed.
   </para>
  </sect3>
  <sect3 xml:id="sec-measurement">
   <title>Units of measurement</title>
   <para>
    You may use abbreviations of common units of measurement.
    For more information on units of measurement, see
    <xref linkend="sec-number"/>.
   </para>
  </sect3>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec-capitalization">
  <title>Capitalization of headings and titles</title>
  <sect3 xml:id="sec-capitalization-sentence">
   <title>Most titles: sentence-style capitalization</title>
   <para>
    Sentence-style capitalization is the most common capitalization used in
    &suse; documentation.
    When using sentence-style capitalization, only proper nouns and the first
    letter of the first word of a phrase are capitalized.
    Apply sentence-style capitalization to all running text and all types of
    headings and titles that are part of the document content.
    An example for sentence-style capitalization is
    <quote>Ceph core components</quote>.
   </para>
  </sect3>
  <sect3 xml:id="sec-capitalization-title">
   <title>Document titles: title-style capitalization</title>
   <para>
    For document titles, such as book, article, and set titles, use
    title-style capitalization.
    This capitalization style is explained in <citetitle>The Chicago Manual of
    Style</citetitle>, 8.167.
    A simplified version of these rules is below:
   </para>
   <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Capitalize the first and the last word.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Write articles in lowercase. Articles are: <emphasis>the</emphasis>,
      <emphasis>a</emphasis>, and <emphasis>an</emphasis>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Write prepositions in lowercase unless they are used with a verb
      (<quote>Logging In</quote>) or in a noun (<quote>The On
      Button</quote>). Prepositions are for example: <emphasis>up</emphasis>,
      <emphasis>in</emphasis>, <emphasis>of</emphasis>,
      <emphasis>through</emphasis>, and <emphasis>between</emphasis>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Write certain conjunctions in lowercase: <emphasis>and</emphasis>,
      <emphasis>but</emphasis>, <emphasis>for</emphasis>,
      <emphasis>nor</emphasis>, and <emphasis>or</emphasis>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Write <emphasis>as</emphasis> and <emphasis>to</emphasis> in lowercase.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Capitalize everything that is not mentioned above.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </orderedlist>
   <para>
    Examples for title-style capitalization are
    <quote>Deployment Guide</quote> (book title) or <quote>Kernel Module
    Packages for SUSE-Based Distributions</quote> (article title).
   </para>
  </sect3>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec-comma">
  <title>Commas</title>
  <para>
   Use commas between all items in a series of three or more elements. For
   example, write <quote>a, b, and c.</quote> Use commas around phrases like
   <emphasis>for example</emphasis> and <emphasis>that is</emphasis>.
   Introductory phrases at the beginning of a sentence are normally followed
   by a comma. For example, <quote>Before using YaST Online Update,
   configure a network connection.</quote>
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec-contraction">
  <title>Contractions</title>
  <para>
   Do not use contractions, unless you are purposefully writing a casual
   document.
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec-dash">
  <title>Dashes</title>
  <para>
   Use en dashes (&ndash;) between numbers in a range in tables and
   figures.
  </para>
  <para>
   For punctuation, use em dashes (&mdash;). Do not surround em dashes
   with spaces. Use em dashes sparingly.
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec-end-sentence">
  <title>End of sentence punctuation</title>
  <para>
   End sentences in a period. Avoid using exclamation marks. Restrict
   question marks to question and answer sections.
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec-file-language">
  <title>File and directory names</title>
  <para>
   Under Linux, objects like directories, printers, or flash disks are all
   considered files. Therefore, the naming and markup conventions are the
   same for <quote>drives</quote> (for example, hard disks, CD-ROM drives),
   directories, or files.
  </para>
  <para>
   The layout for file names and directory names is the same. See the
   following example:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     In general, use forward slashes (<literal>/</literal>) to separate
     nested directory or file names. If you are describing actions performed
     on Windows&thrdmrk; systems and within a Windows-native file system,
     use backward slashes (<literal>\</literal>) instead.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     In general, when giving absolute paths, always start with a leading
     slash to indicate the root of the file system. If you are describing
     actions performed on Windows systems and within a Windows-native file
     system, do not add a leading slash to absolute paths.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Use a trailing slash to distinguish between a file and a
     directory. If the distinction is important in the current context, in
     addition comment on it in the accompanying or surrounding running text.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   Most Linux file systems are case-sensitive. Use capitals exactly as they
   appear in the file system. For more information on markup aspects, see
   <xref linkend="sec-other-external"/> and
   <xref linkend="sec-file-markup"/>.
  </para>
  <para>
   When it is necessary to refer to file extensions, such as in compound
   words like <quote>PDF file</quote>, always capitalize the extension.
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec-bias">
  <title>Gender bias</title>
  <para>
   Avoid indicating gender in your documentation. If possible, use plural to
   allow use of <quote>they</quote> as the pronoun. Otherwise, use <quote>he
   or she.</quote>
  </para>
  <para>
   For naming of example items, refer to <xref linkend="sec-name"/>. For
   more information on how to avoid gender bias, refer to <citetitle>The
   Chicago Manual of Style</citetitle>, 5.43.
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec-heading">
  <title>Headings</title>
  <para>
   When writing a descriptive section, use a noun-based heading title,
   for example, <quote>Concepts of Software</quote>.
   When writing a task-orientated section, use a verb in gerund, for example,
   <quote>Installing Software</quote>.
  </para>
  <para>
   Keep headings short and simple. Do not use both an acronym and the
   expanded form in a heading. Make sure that headlines in a chapter
   follow the same pattern.
  </para>
  <para>
   For advice on how to nest sections, refer to
   <xref linkend="sec-outline-level"/>.
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec-language-list">
  <title>Lists</title>
  <para>
   For information about creating lists, see <xref linkend="sec-list"/>.
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec-number">
  <title>Numbers and measurements</title>
  <para>
   Write the integers zero through nine as words. Use numerals for all other
   numbers.
  </para>
  <para>
   When the unit of a measurement is abbreviated, always use numerals for
   the number. In measurements, add a non-breaking space (
   <tag class="genentity">nbsp</tag>
   ) between the numeral and its corresponding unit abbreviation.
  </para>
  <para>
   For more information, refer to <citetitle>The Chicago Manual of
   Style</citetitle> 9.6 and 9.16.
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec-possessive">
  <title>Possessives</title>
  <para>
   Do not use possessives of acronyms and trademarked terms. Avoid
   possessives of inanimate objects.
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec-prefix">
  <title>Prefixes</title>
  <para>
   Add a hyphen after the prefix to prefixed words only if:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The last letter of the prefix and the first letter of the word are the
     same.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     You foresee misunderstandings. For example, there is a difference in
     meaning between <quote>recreate</quote> and <quote>re-create</quote>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec-semicolon">
  <title>Semicolons</title>
  <para>
   Avoid using semicolons to join sentences. You may use semicolons in place
   of commas in very complicated series.
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec-slash">
  <title>Slashes</title>
  <para>
   Do not use slashes except when they are part of a standard technical
   term, such as <emphasis>TCP/IP</emphasis> or
   <emphasis>client/server</emphasis>.
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec-structure-sentence">
  <title>Sentence structure</title>
  <para>
   Form clear and direct sentences with 20 words or less. Avoid complicated
   clauses. Make sure that the relationship between subject, verb, and
   object are clear. Avoid joining sentences with semicolons. Avoid ending
   sentences with prepositions.
  </para>
  <para>
   Avoid using parentheses. Where they are necessary, move them to the end
   of the sentence. Never nest parentheses.
  </para>
  <para>
   Always let the reader know the objective of an action before describing
   the action itself. As an example, write: <quote>To restore world peace,
   click <guimenu>Shake Hands</guimenu>.</quote>
   <remark>sknorr 2014-01-07: it's hard to take this quote seriously.
        Find something better.</remark>
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec-tense">
  <title>Tense</title>
  <para>
   Use the simple present tense. Apply the simple present tense even to
   sentences with <quote>if</quote> or <quote>when</quote> clauses:
   <quote>If this happens, go there.</quote>
  </para>
  <para>
   Prerequisites of an action should be expressed in the present tense as
   well: <quote>Glibc is installed.</quote> In some cases, no verb is
   necessary before the prerequisite of an action: <quote>a 1&nbsp;GHz
   processor or better.</quote>
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec-tone">
  <title>Tone and voice</title>
  <para>
   Maintain a professional tone. Do not use contractions, except in casual
   documents. Do not use humor. Be honest and avoid absolutes and
   exaggerations, but focus on positive aspects.
  </para>
  <para>
   Use second person (<quote>you</quote>) to refer to the reader. Normally,
   the reader is the user or administrator who performs the actions described.
   Do not overuse <quote>you.</quote> It is often understood, especially in
   directions.
  </para>
  <para>
   Where possible, use active voice. In active voice, the subject of the
   sentence performs the verb. For example, <quote>The root user performs
   administrative tasks</quote> is active voice. <quote>Administrative tasks
   are performed by the root user</quote> is passive voice.
  </para>
  <para>
   Use passive voice if there is no emphasis on the object of the verb or if
   the performer of the action is unknown. <quote>A Samba server must be
   configured in the network</quote> is an example of proper use of passive
   voice. The emphasis is on the server, not on the person configuring it.
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec-trademark">
  <title>Trademarks</title>
  <para>
   Most products referenced in the documentation are trademarked. Follow
   these rules when dealing with these terms:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Never use trademarks in headings.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Only use the marked version on the first occurrence of the product name
     in a chapter.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Only use the &reg;, &tm;, or &sm; marks for &suse; products.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Use an * (asterisk) for all service marks or trademarks of third-party
     companies. This acknowledges the service mark or trademark of the other
     company. It also protects &suse; if the protection of the brand changes
     in any way.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   For more information on markup aspects, see <xref linkend="sec-product"/>.
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec-ui-item-language">
  <title>User interface items</title>
  <para>
   When referring to labels of user interface items, do not include ending
   punctuation such as <literal>…</literal> or <literal>:</literal>.
   Whenever possible, refer to user interface items without identifying them
   as any special type of element. For example, use <quote>click
   <guimenu>OK</guimenu></quote> rather than <quote>click the
   <guimenu>OK</guimenu> button.</quote> However, complex dialogs may
   require more specific wording.
  </para>
  <para>
   For instructions concerning markup, refer to
   <xref linkend="sec-ui-item-markup"/>.
  </para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 xml:id="sec-quotation">
  <title>Quotations</title>
  <para>
   Use quotations to quote from sources, such as books.
   In other cases, avoid using quotation marks.
   Do not use irony and do not use quotation marks to mark irony.
   In the case of computer input, computer output, and user
   interface elements, use more appropriate markup. See also
   <xref linkend="sec-command-line"/> and
   <xref linkend="sec-ui-item-markup"/>.
  </para>
  <para>
   To create quotations, use the
   <tag class="emptytag">quote</tag>
   element, as it is easier to localize than hardcoded quotation marks and
   always provides typographic quotes.
  </para>
  <para>
   Punctuation directly following the quoted text should be included within
   the quotation marks, as illustrated in <xref linkend="ex-quote"/>.
  </para>
  <example xml:id="ex-quote">
   <title>Quote</title>
   <para>
    <quote>Suds may froth,</quote> the sign reads.
   </para>
  </example>
 </sect2>
</sect1>
