<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="sec-webwriting">
 <title>Writing for the Web</title>

 <para>
  Create engaging and informative content that helps your audience and is
  optimized for the Web.
 </para>

 <section xml:id="sec-topical">
  <title>Topical structure</title>
  <para>
   The most important thing to do with your Web copy is to help users get
   answers to their questions as soon as possible. To achieve this, we
   recommend the modular approach of topic-based authoring where documentation
   is created and maintained in chunks, subsequently referred to as topics.
  </para>
  <para>
   Topics have the sole purpose of supporting users in their tasks. Each topic
   focuses on one specific subject and has one distinct purpose. We write
   topics in a way that they can stand alone as well as in context with other
   topics. They should also be reusable in different contexts.
  </para>
  <para>
   Recommendations:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Put your most important information first. Users typically decide if they
     are going to stay on your page within 3&ndash;5 seconds. Make sure your
     copy helps users understand the big picture right away.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Write for scanners. Help readers find the answer to their question. Create
     headlines that are clear and to the point. Break long headlines into a
     heading and sub-head. Ask yourself: Is it easy to see the benefit of the
     page with a quick glance?
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Organize content logically. Layer and break up your content into sections
     to help users find answers at a glance.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="sec-seo">
  <title>Writing SEO-friendly content</title>
  <para>
   SEO, or Search Engine Optimization, is the strategy to attract organic
   (unpaid) traffic that originates from online search and refers to visitors
   landing on the Web site. When it comes to SEO, content is key. Here are some
   insights to help you create and design the content that will rank high in
   search engines.
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Brainstorm and research keywords</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      To learn what type of content search engines deem best for a specific
      keyword, search the phrases you want to rank for. Bear in mind the
      approved &suse; documentation terminology.
     </para>
     <para>
      At the same time, do not stuff your content with keywords. The keyword
      ratio for an article should be 2&ndash;4%, that is, 8&ndash;10 keywords
      per 500 words.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Structure your content in a way that is easy for users to scan</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Structuring your headings in a hierarchy can make a larger content piece
      easily scannable while helping search engines understand the context of
      your content. For example:
     </para>
<screen>&lt;H1&gt; Dealing with Boot and Installation Problems
&lt;H2&gt; Problems Booting
	&lt;H3&gt; Solution 1
	&lt;H3&gt; Solution 2
&lt;H2&gt; Problems Installing
	&lt;H3&gt; Solution 1
	&lt;H3&gt; Solution 2
  </screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Create concise and meaningful title tags and meta descriptions</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Search engines pull the title tag, or meta title, from H1, and the meta
      description from the abstract. The number of characters is limited, and
      the recommended length for meta titles is 55&ndash;65 characters.
      However, they must not be shorter than 29 characters. Be sure to optimize your
      headings wherever appropriate by integrating keywords, such as product
      names, into them. The optimal length for meta descriptions is 145&ndash;155 characters.
     </para>
     <para>
      Product names are known for their extra length, so effective page titles
      and meta descriptions may require the use of abbreviations. From the
      search engine perspective, it can be helpful to mention the abbreviation
      within the content by adding the abbreviation in parenthesis after the
      first use of the term.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Link from (and to) your content</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Links are critical to establishing the authority and relevance of your
      content. The two most important types of links are:
     </para>
     <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Internal links lead to and from other pages within the same domain and
        help establish the relationship between two pieces of content. Internal
        linking helps search engines discover new pages on the Web site and
        index them.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Inbound links lead to your content piece from a different domain (for
        example, SAP.com to SUSE.com).
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </orderedlist>
     <para>
      External links to high-quality, creditable Web sites help increase the
      validity of your own Web site. The better the links, the higher the page
      ranks in search results.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Optimize images by adding alt text</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Be sure to add alternative text whenever you use images. This practice
      allows search engines to understand the context of your images and index
      them more accurately. It also improves the accessibility of the Web site.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="sec-writing-global">
  <title>Writing for a global audience</title>
  <para>
   Remember that every document is a potential candidate for localization (translation). 
   Make sure the document’s original English content is correct and clear. Simplicity, 
   clarity and direct prose are essential.
   </para>
   <para>
   Recommendations:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
   <para>
   Keep sentences short. Shorter sentences help translators and target audience to 
   better understand the content.
   </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
   <para>
   Be consistent. Stick to the terminology and use the same sentence structure for 
   similar content. Use the same sentences for repetitive texts. This helps to improve
   the translation memory leverage.
   </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
   <para>
   Use proofreading and review options. Have your content reviewed to detect 
   misunderstandings in advance.
   </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
    Keep it clear. Make clear statements and avoid <quote>should,</quote>
    <quote>could</quote> and similar unprecise words.
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para>
     Mark non-translatable text. Use tags as defined in <xref linkend="sec-taglist"/>
     or use the ITS tag feature to mark all content that should not be translated 
     (for more information, see <xref linkend="sec-taglist-ITS"/>).
     Use entities for product names, example names, etc. Always mark code 
     as such so that it is not translated.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
   <para>
   Write for the world (if possible). Do not use country-specific words and examples.
   Use common international examples instead.
   </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
   <para>
   Use only as many graphics as needed. As each graphic or screenshot needs
   to be localized as well, keep it to the minimum.
   </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
   <para>
   Do not break sentences. Do not use hard breaks within a sentence.
   </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
   <para>
   Do not break your sentence with lists. For example, do not structure the 
   phrase like this:
   </para>
   <screen>You can use the following commands:
   -a
   -z
   -b
   to start the system update.
   </screen>
   <para>
   Keep the sentence together instead:</para>
   <screen>
   To start the system update, you can use the following commands:
   -a
   -z
   -b
   </screen>
   </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
 </section>
</chapter>
