<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<sect1 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="sec-smartdocs">
 <title>Working with Smart Docs</title>

 <para>
  Smart Docs represent the modular approach to documentation whose goal is producing sets of 
  adaptable, solution-based, easy-to-find and reusable documents.  
 </para>

 <para>
  Smart Documentation consists of smaller information units with the following characteristics:
 </para>
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <formalpara>
    <title>Self-contained</title>
    <para>
     Each information unit stands for itself, including requirements, context, instructions and FAQs. 
    </para>
   </formalpara>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <formalpara>
    <title>Cover one distinct topic</title>
    <para>
     Rather than covering a complete technology or a set of problems, each information unit 
     serves one distinct purpose. Five different types of information units are provided:
    </para>
    </formalpara>
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Assembly builds the actual article from the components listed below.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Task topics instruct the user how to perform certain tasks.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Concept topics explain underlying concepts to the users.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Reference topics inform the user about basic facts (settings, options, parameters, etc.).
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Glue topics help navigate complex topics and provide links to related information 
      (combine texts or structures that do not fit into any other category). Typical 
      glue topics include <quote>For more information</quote> and <quote>What's next</quote> sections. 
      Use glue topics to also add an additional layer of navigation to your article.
     </para>
     </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
   <formalpara>
    <title>Reused in different contexts</title>
    <para>
     Task, concept and reference information units can be reused in different context. Content units 
     (articles) are built by bundling these into dedicated assembly files.
    </para>
   </formalpara>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
  <para>To create a Smart Docs project, use the templates for the assembly and its topical components 
  that are provided in the Doc Modular repository at <link xlink:href="https://github.com/SUSE/doc-modular/tree/main/templates"/>.</para>

</sect1>
